Good evening. Turn them on. Good evening
everybody.
DJ, could we have in-house audio up just
a smidge if it's possible?
David
Maybe
just to try just because I'm usually a
little bit louder on the when I'm this
close.
I'll wait till I can see him.
How about now? That's perfect. Thank
you. I appreciate it. I don't want to
yell. All right. Good evening. Uh I now
call this uh July 22nd, 2025 meeting of
Lancaster City Council to order. This
meeting and its participants are being
recorded. Please take a moment to
silence your phones and your devices if
you haven't done so already. Uh during
this meeting there there will be several
opportunities for public comment. The
first is a general public comment period
for residents that have registered in
advance to speak about items that are
not on the agenda. Residents may also
comment on individual items on our
legislative agenda. That's section nine
uh on our agenda this evening. And
finally, a second public comment period
will be at the end of our agenda for any
other speakers wishing to address
council. All speakers will be reminded
to begin with their name and block of
residence for our meeting record and
address their comments toward council.
Please be advised that public comment is
not question answer period. All comments
are limited to three minutes per
speaker. Uh to keep time, I'll be using
a timer light here. When it green to
three minutes is begun. When it blinks
yellow, there's one minute remaining.
And when it blinks red, three minutes
has been exhausted. If a speaker
continues after three minutes, I will uh
kindly ask that they end their comment.
I appreciate everyone's cooperation to
maintain order and equal time. Speakers
addressing city council and members of
the audience will be expected to conduct
themselves in an orderly manner and
remain respectful of others. And now,
for all that are willing and able,
please rise for the pledge of
allegiance.
United States
and justice for all.
>> Mr. Harris, would you please call the
role of members?
>> Yes, Madam President. Mr. M
>> here.
>> Mr. Roya
>> Mr. Please
>> here.
>> Miss Craig
>> here. Miss Diaz
>> here,
>> Mr. Hirs
>> and President B
>> here.
>> Our first item in front of us this
evening is the approval of the minutes
of our July 8th, 2025 agenda. Uh,
counselors. Um, oh, I will hear a motion
for that.
>> Motion to approve.
>> Second.
>> Thank you. We have a motion and a second
for our meeting minutes. Any counselors
have comments on the minutes?
>> Hearing none, Mr. Harris?
>> Mr.
I
>> Mr. Roy
>> I
>> Mr. Glee
>> Miss Craig
>> I
>> Miss Diaz
>> Mr. Hersh
>> I
>> and
>> President Be
>> I
>> The next item on our agenda is
proclamations, honors, awards and
resolutions of recognition confirming
Mr. Harris that we have none of those
this evening. Is that right?
>> We do not have any this evening.
>> Thank you very much. uh councilors uh
with um unless there is any specific
objection I would like to move the
report of president of council to this
point in the agenda.
Great. I appreciate that.
Um given that uh many of you are here
tonight regarding the planned data
center on Greenfield Road, I would like
to begin with some updates that are
pertinent. Um the uh these updates for
council and the public uh were shared
during an earlier press briefing this
afternoon. It was attended by the mayor
and representatives from Cararissa
Technology Parks and Wilson and Turner
Construction. Um this is particularly
important. As of at least 5:30, I hadn't
seen any coverage on this and I think
it's important that the information is
disseminated to the public.
So here is a rundown. You're going to
hear me talk a lot, so get ready. Uh,
two existing indu industrial sites at
216 Greenfield Road and 1375 Harrisburg
Pike are being developed by Carissa
Technology Parks and Machine Investment
Group. The construction is being managed
by Wilson and Turner Construction. Only
one of those properties, 216 Greenfield
Road, has any active building permits
under review. These are not definitive
there are not definitive plans for 1375
Harrisburg Pike at this time.
Construction at Greenfield Road has
begun and is expected to be completed in
summer of 2027.
Um, the city is required to comply with
existing legislation and state law in
dealing with property owners and their
use. This includes the city's zoning
ordinance, subdivision ordinance, and
land development ordinance that complies
with the PA municipalities planning code
and all state laws. Um, a note on
zoning. Uh, as you may know, the city
determined that zoning was allowed by
right, meaning the current zoning
applies to the proposed use. The future
land use map on our future Lancaster
also designates these areas of the city
as appropriate for highdensity
industrial and regional commercial
development. I want to also note that
changes to the zoning ordinance require
a lengthy process, including review and
approval by the county planning
commission, several public meetings, and
a public hearing. Uh, and under the
matter of the building permit, based
upon the building permit applications
that were submitted to the city for 216
Greenfield Road, none of the work
currently being performed or planned
under those permits constitutes a land
development or subdivision subject to
planning commission approval. If future
work extends beyond the existing
building's footprint, the land
development process would be applicable.
Uh, o city oversight. There has been and
continues to be considerable review and
oversight done by city staff, including
building permit applications uh
reviewing to reviewed to asssure
conditional uh approval and compliance
with all applicable codes, including
construction, demolition, and fire
mitigation. Uh updates on water usage.
These sites will not rely on large
volumes of water for cooling purposes.
In contrast to other data centers, these
sites will use fans for air cooling.
Additionally, existing ordinances
protect the city from having to provide
water to any customer under any
circumstances, most especially if we do
not have the capacity to do so. I want
to reiterate, and this is important,
that existing ordinances already ensure
that we are not required to provide
water in the instances where we do not
have capacity. Uh, a note on power.
Carissa Technology Parks is working
closely with PPL to asssure electrical
needs are met without impact to their
customers. They reported this afternoon,
Carissa is paying for upgrades to
electrical electrical substations on the
Greenfield property to reinforce the
power grid. PPL is building a new
switchyard as well as adding resiliency
to the local grid. Um, council will
continue to monitor these updates from
that utility. A note on fire safety.
Fire Chief Hutchinson has been involved
in the review to ensure that the
state-of-the-art fire prevention systems
are in place and ensure that our
firefighters are prepared for any
emergency response.
Notes on noise. The developers have
assessed the potential for noise impact
at Greenfield Road and they have found
through their review that the data
center will be noise neutral, meaning
the noise generated by the data center
will be at the level of or less than the
current noise level at the site. This is
yet to be independently evaluated by the
city. Council will also continue to
ensure the public is updated on this
matter. Um, a note on jobs that was
shared at the press conference this
afternoon. Uh, the city is pleased that
a local construction company, Wolson, is
undertaking this project um, generating
local employment of between 600 and
a,000 construction jobs as well as 150
approximate new permanent jobs uh, in
Lancaster. Um, I do want to make notes
on city benefits that were shared at the
conference. The productive use of these
sites will have tangible benefits to the
city's revenues and thus the taxpayers.
The sale and redevelopment of these
properties impact the real estate
transfer tax, assessed value for real
estate taxes and building permit
building permit revenue. Um, another
note in addition to the tangible
economic benefits um from the city on
the city's revenues, uh, Mayor Sarra uh
stated she will be negotiating a
community benefit agreement that will
demonstrate that Carissa Technology
Parks and its tenants are committed to
being good neighbors here in Lancaster
and more details are will be forthcoming
and council will monitor those updates.
I also want to make a note about
opportunities for future engagement on
this matter. Carissa announced their
intention to hold a town hall in the
future, so directly with the developer
to discuss more details as they become
available related to power uh sources,
etc. So, we will uh continue to push out
updates as we learn from them when they
will hold those. That concludes my
council president's report this evening.
Members of council, thank you for
allowing me to move that forward uh in
our agenda this evening.
We will now move into our first public
comment period. This is reserved for
residents who have contacted the city
prior to this meeting to request the
opportunity to address council. Uh this
was before the 2pm deadline uh to get
our meeting materials together. Duration
of comments are again are limited to
three minutes. I've asked Mr. Harris to
please put a list of those who have
registered for public comment in advance
on the screen so that you can know when
you're next and proceed to the
microphone there. Uh just a note, please
begin with your name and block of
residence for our meeting record. Um,
and as you might be the first person to
reach the microphone, you may need to
turn it on. It may already be on. Um,
and I'll be keeping time. Thank you so
much,
Mr. Harris. Our first speaker.
>> Our first speaker is Tony Hopkins.
>> Good evening, sir.
>> Can you just make sure uh there might be
a button or not?
>> It's okay. We're working on borrowed
tech.
>> There we go. Thank you so much,
>> Madame President. Madame Mayor, um I uh
am an well I'm a now a retired attorney.
I practiced law here in the city for
many many years both for a rather
prominent firm and I had my own office
for 10 or 11 years on Walnut Street. I'd
like to begin my comments by paying my
respects to Councilman Amed. I've known
the councilman since he was a
12-year-old boy playing uh right guard
for the East Pete Bulldog football team.
My son was playing right tackle on that
team. So, Councilman, it's good to see
you raised up to a position of prestige.
I never doubted you would achieve that.
Um,
so my comments about traffic. Uh, the
other about two weeks ago, I was driving
north on Mary Street. Um, I I want to
say uh I went home on Wall Street every
day for 30 plus years. Um,
so I was trying to turn left on the
Waller Street and I couldn't see a
thing. Okay. I uh had a conversation
with one of your staffers when I brought
this to the attention of the clerk and
um she told me that the city traffic
plan believes or is drawn in such a way
as to quote unquote daylight those
intersections so that people can see
oncoming traffic. I'm here to tell you
it's a fiasco. Okay. I waited and waited
and waited. I eventually nosed my way
out. And as I looked to my right, there
were three cars doing at least 35 miles
an hour coming up that incline on Walnut
Street. Everybody accelerates to come up
Walnut Street. Uh if I had waited two
more seconds, there would have been a
fourc car collision at that
intersection. If I had been crossing
Walnut Street, it would have been a
T-bone collision. Okay. Since then, I've
made it my business to pay more
attention when I drive out Walnut
Street. And I'm going to tell you that s
that problem exists at every
intersection you have on Walnut Street
and Lemon Street except the ones where
you have traffic lights. Uh you've
daylighted those intersections by
removing one parking place. That is near
that is not nearly sufficient. It is
literally impossible to see the oncoming
traffic heading west on Walnut Street
pretty much at every intersection you
have. It's extremely hazardous
situation. Uh, I will tell you
furthermore that um conversation I've
had with a a young person, a young woman
uh who te tells me that um a lot of the
young moms on those streets are
extremely concerned about the speed of
the traffic coming up on the street and
the uh inability to see at
intersections. It's an extremely
extremely hazardous situation.
complicated by the bike lane and the uh
xed out lane you have so cars doors can
open and not interfere with the bike
lane. I'm not an anti-bicycle guy. When
I was a young man uh I had a very
significantly high level bike. I put it
on my shoulder. I flew to England and
bicycle. Okay. So this is a severe
situation. You need to pay attention to
it. Thank you.
>> Thank you sir.
>> Mr. Mr. Harris, our next speaker.
>> Next speaker is Mary Mlan.
>> Thank you. And just for as a reminder,
just you're already doing it. Please
begin with your block. Thank you.
>> 123 Christian Street. And
the concerns
come right into the mic. Thank you.
Uh and uh I know that the one is going
to be cooled by air instead of water,
but air cooling uh
could mean significant noise pollution
for anyone live living within a quarter
mile of it. The decibb reach well over
those considered safe for humans near
air cooled data centers. Lancaster city
zoning told me today that in practice
they can only take the word of the and
can't determine ahead of time if the
business will be noisy. In fact, city
zoning said that the data center company
met with city officials and one of the
things they discussed was noise. The
city was convinced by the response of
the company that there would be no noise
problem. But this is just based on what
they want to say.
In fact, if you look at the other data
centers around the country, noise is a
problem.
The city Okay. The city noise ordinance
can come into play only after the center
is built and operating, at which point
it would be impossible for residents to
get any enforcement. And PA state has no
noise laws that might help.
And I couldn't tell from what you did in
your said in your update whether city
officials have promised tax breaks to
the data centers. There are 170
properties in the city that have local
tax exemptions, mostly hospital, church,
and school.
The state of PA is about to pass bills
with incentives to lure AI data centers
to our state. Most or some
municipalities and states have offered
tax breaks and regretted it later
because they are difficult to end.
Washington state approved tax breaks for
data centers without public input, I
might add, and
they
uh are suffering
that loss of revenue for very few jobs
that were created by having the data
centers there.
The typical data center employs 50 to
200 permanent technical and maintenance
jobs. I know they told you something
like up to a thousand. That's not what
the usual one is.
And so if the data centers proposed here
in Lancaster do not pay local taxes,
there will be no value to having them
here other than ridding ourselves of the
problem of an empty warehouse. residents
may find themselves funding new
transmission lines down the road as has
happened in some municipalities.
Something else to think about, the city
approved demolition of the Greenfield
site building June 30th, but if the
approval was made public, it was not
front page news as perhaps it should
have been.
>> Miss Mlan, we've reached three minutes.
>> Okay, thank you.
>> Feels like a lack of trans
Mr. Harris, our next speaker, please.
>> Next speaker is Jackie Snider.
>> Miss Jackie Snyder, present this
evening.
>> Okay, Mr. Harris, our next speaker.
>> And next is Rachel Bear.
>> Thank you.
>> Is Rachel with us this evening?
>> We will move. Our next speaker
>> is Amy Ernst.
>> There we go.
>> Good evening.
>> Hi, my name is Amy Ernst. I live on the
800 block of Columbia Avenue in the
city. Um, I'm here to propose a textual
amendment to the zoning ordinance to
reclassify data centers moving forward
as digital infrastructure facilities
permitted only in general industrial
zones subject to conditional use.
We all know these are not wholesale
trade and storage facilities. They don't
use they don't store anything
traditional and they don't do it in a
traditional way and wholesale trade and
storage facilities require one of the
lowest levels of oversight.
These types of centers require far
higher levels of oversight. It's like
calling them storage facilities and
requiring such low levels of oversight
is like calling a toxic waste facility
storage because it stores toxic waste.
Whether it's a massive drain on the
power grid or water supply that
residents might carry the weight of or
the alarming health effects already
being seen in communities across the US
from their cooling fans and there will
be more effects to come. This is the
wild west for for these companies. Um
but these data centers do have the power
to to have a really negative impact on
this incredible city. Other counties are
starting to take action. The language
that I was focusing on, which I sent in
emails earlier today, um is a digital
infrastructure amendment is from
Frederick County, Maryland, where
they're not letting these companies bait
them and harm their communities. Um I
know people, many people here today have
worked really hard over the past 20
years to build this city into one of the
most desirable small cities to live in.
Please don't let it be destroyed by
letting big tech walk all over us.
They'll fly in their specialists. They
won't create many new jobs here. The
construction jobs will be temporary.
They'll take what they need. They'll
make huge profits and they'll just leave
the city in its wake. As I said before,
these are not traditional storage
facilities. So, I am proposing this
textual amendment. Whether it can apply
to these data centers or any moving
forward, they should not be classified
as wholesale trade and storage and they
need new classification with higher
oversight and conditional use
permitting.
>> Thank you.
Mr. Harris, our next speaker, please.
>> Our next speaker is Jontel Toland.
>> I'll just remind folks we have the list
in the order they were received on the
screen behind us. Good evening.
>> Uh good evening. Uh Jontel Tolen, first
and only block of uh Wise. Um, I don't
come here often. When I'm here, you
usually know there's a problem. Uh,
there's tons of people here. Uh,
councelor Beay, I heard what you said
and thank you for saying that at the
beginning. Um, but I still think that
many people here are probably still
skeptical and concerned. Um, and I hope
that there is some transparency that
continues to happen going forward. Um,
and I hope that people continue to come
and and check on them and see what goes
on. Um, I I had a lot of things that I
wanted to say. Uh, and I think I will
hold off on some of them. Um, but I did
email you all as well. Uh,
I think that we're all still very
concerned about the impacts and the
things that you said still didn't really
do much for me. I'm still very concerned
and uh I would like to see you guys
address this more and and do your own
research as to the impacts of uh
Memphis, Tennessee, for example, um and
what's been going on there and the town
hall meetings that have been held uh
with no accountability and no
transparency whatsoever after the fact.
and
you giving the spiel of what you just
said. It's it's kind of it's to me it
sounds like fluff. Um, and I believe I
only heard in reference to like
Greenville Road and I think I I there's
there's another site on Harrisburg Pike
that's being looked at, right? I just
think that there should be a a a big
firm stance that is a collaboration
between the community and city council
because we really have to cut this off
at the head before anything else goes
any further. I don't think that we
should even be considering that any of
these facilities are anywhere in the
county. Um so I'll keep an eye out.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Tolen.
Just for
clarification, and I appreciate your
words, um the information that was
provided at my report at the top of the
meeting was a way to disseminate the
information that was given at the press
event earlier tonight. Um
not necessarily a a judgment statement,
but the factual information that was
shared. So, we will continue. And I I do
want to and I think I've um reiterated
this to some of you who may have reached
out per to me personally that members of
council are interested in in preserving
the public safety uh in uh resources and
interest in this and have been working
um as we've been made aware of this
which was not terribly long ago. Um but
I want to ensure that there is continued
oversight. So but I appreciate your
words and thank you for that. Mr. Mr.
Harris, our next speaker,
>> our next speaker is Brian Nelson.
>> Evening. Uh, as uh, Mr. Nelson is coming
forward, I'll I'll just remind everyone
that the names are on on the screen in
the list in the order in which they will
rece were received. Uh, so the next
folks can be ready. Good evening.
>> Um, hi, I'm Brian Nelson. I live on the
100 block of East Lemon and um, I wanted
to talk about the plan data center as
well. Um, I think that I have an issue
with two major corporations telling us
what will and will not be good for our
citizens. I think that's up for us to
decide. And I think that we have these
data center companies coming here trying
to use up all their power because they
don't think we have enough to fight
back. And I think that I have an issue
with that. Um, my major issue is uh to
use computers, you have to use a lot of
energy. You create a lot of heat that
burns a lot of carbon. and they're going
to set that off into Lancaster County
with these planned data centers um in
these areas that are going to create
noise pollution whether you like it or
not. And in fact, it takes more energy
to cool these data centers than they
create computing power. So there's
nothing about these data centers that
screams energy efficiency to me. And
we're already getting hit with hikes
from PPL. Um I don't believe them when
they say I'm not going to get a hike. I
don't believe that for a second. And I
think that is on you guys as city
councilors to actually what they said is
take a stand and let us know whether or
not you agree or disagree with having
this data center in our community
because I think that the community right
now is ready to tell you that they don't
want it and I think that that's on you
guys to do your job and make sure that
they've been heard and that's all they
have to say.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Mr. Harris, our next speaker, please.
Our next speaker is Mimi Shapiro.
>> Didn't think I saw Mimi this evening.
>> Mr. Harris, our next speaker then.
>> And next is Emma Burgess.
>> Thank you.
Good evening.
>> Hello. Um yeah, like you said, my name
is Emma Burgess. I live on the 600th
block of West Fine Street. Um and I hold
a master's degree in electrical
engineering. Um I really thank you, um
President Beay, for the updates. I think
that was really helpful context. Um, and
actually I really appreciate the
comments by Brian. I'm kind of going to
provide a little bit more context in
terms of the numbers. Um, in three
minutes I really only have time to talk
about the utility impacts of building a
data center. Um, I think you've probably
read the L&P article from July 16th, but
let me quickly reiterate a few points.
Um, the data center is estimated to
consume 100 megawatts of power and would
run 247. That is 70,000 megawatts
megawatt hours per month. The average
Pennsylvania household, according to the
EIA in 2022, consume consumes 854
kilwatt hours per month. Um, which means
that the data center would consume the
energy equivalent of 85,000 homes in
Lancaster on the low end. There are
21,000 homes in Lancaster City.
According to the Census Bureau, adding a
data center would use the energy
equivalent of four times the entirety of
Lancaster City houses on the low end. On
the high end, it would use the energy
equivalent of the entirety of Lancaster
County households. Um, really quick, I'd
like to note that the L&P article
misleadingly gives numbers for one
megawatt, which is 100 to 300 times less
than this proposed data center, which
they say would power 400 to 900 homes
for a year. And using recent data from
the EIA, I get 850 to 2,500 homes, which
is twice as much. I spoke to the
reporter, his neighbors were but based
on 2001 figures, um, and had some
assumptions in there. After speaking
together, he agreed that the numbers I
just told you were correct. Um,
regarding the water cooling to fans
cooling, um, I think that would pro
increase the amount of, uh, energy used
there. Um, either way, that puts immense
stress on a power grid that is already
getting increasingly expensive for us.
Um, like Brian said, from January 2020
to today, electricity rates have gone up
by 50% according to PPL's own data
records. Um, across news sources and
climate advocacy organizations, experts
always agree that when data centers are
built within an existing power grid,
everyday consumers always pay the price.
Lancaster City residents um are already
struggling to pay those bills. This
would make things worse. Um, it's not
just the cost to increase the power
grid, it's the cost to maintain a much
much much larger power grid. Um, and we
have no guarantee that Carissa is going
Cararissa um is going to pay that cost
forever. Um, Senator McCormick has been
touting the economic benefits of this
data center. Um, but I ask you to
consider, council, are 150 jobs worth
the decadesl long price that Lancaster
residents are going to have to pay for
this data data center? And I really have
to ask you to consider to put safeguards
against this kind of development that
jeopardizes the future of Lancastrians
for decades to come. Please consider
public input before allowing us to go
forward. Thank you for your time.
>> Thank you.
Mr. Harris, our next speaker.
>> Next speaker is Dan Wigel.
>> Good evening, sir.
>> All right. Uh, Dan Wigle, uh, the only
block of Clarendon Drive. Um, data
centers are not warehouses. Uh, they do
not merely store products and should not
be classified as wholesale trade and
storage. Data centers consume massive
amounts of dirty fossil fuels. They
pollute the environment and they are
hazardous to the health of those living
nearby. I am not willing to trade my
health, the health of my neighbors, or
the health of the environment for
corporate profits. I hope that each of
you are also unwilling to make that
trade. We are not helpless bystanders to
the corporate profit-driven AI so-called
revolution. We the people have a choice
and we do not want it. This is a
bipartisan consensus with a recent LNP
poll showing more than twice as many
residents opposing the data center as
favoring it. So on a local level, we
must say no to data centers. Let us
choose people, the ones living and
raising families here right now, not
corporate profits. I understand that
saying no to data centers is not easy in
a legal sense. What I ask is this, a
text amendment to the zoning ordinance
to reclassify data centers from their
current status as wholesale trade and
storage. Instead, I propose a new
category, digital infrastructure
facilities, that will require oversight,
regulation, and a lengthy review process
with ample public input prior to any
permits being issued. Regardless of
whether it is too late to stop the first
facility, please act urgently to protect
our community moving forward. Data
centers are a new and unique form of
harm, and they require an appropriate
response. I get that it is a long
process to change the zoning ordinance.
Let's start that process now. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Mr. Harris, our next speaker,
>> our next speaker is Abby Haney.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening. Uh, my name is Abby Haney.
I live on the 600 block of East Madison
Street, and I am like so many others
here about the AI data centers. I have
some major concerns. Um, so I want to
talk a little bit about electrical
usage, but so many of you have already
made really great points and are far
more educated than I am. Um but
Coreweave, which is the same company
that like would operate here, they
actually have um a facility in Denton,
Texas, and it's already been shown that
they've doubled the amount of
electricity used in Denton um using a
majority of the local power system
capacity. These facilities, like others
have mentioned, have to be powered 24
hours a day, 7 days a week, 365 days a
year. And a 100 megawatt facility
consumes as much electricity as 100,000
households annually. Um, and oftentimes
residential users are left footing the
bow for this huge power drain because
power c companies subsidize the cost of
these data centers by passing along rate
increases to residential customers. My
PPNL rate has not gone down in seven
years that I've lived here. So, I can't
imagine that it will then. In regard to
the belief that the building of these
data centers will help the local job
market, um, especially for the
construction industry, I'm old enough to
remember when they said the same thing
about fracking. Um, instead they brought
workers from out of state and then
things when things were all said and
done, these companies would pack up and
leave the community to deal with the
environmental fallout. Um, I saw the
information from the mayor's office that
these plan to be air cooled, not water
cooled. And I just want to ask, can you
confidently say that they'll remain that
way? What happens when this center
inevitably expands and air cooling is no
longer costefficient or effective for
core? I could also talk at length about
how climate change is not going to spare
us and will cause shrinking of our water
tables and that Lancaster has the second
worst air quality in the Mid-Atlantic
and 22nd worst in the country.
I'm calling for a change in zoning laws
like so many others have. Um, this
center falls under wholesale trade and
storage which is outdated and is not
applicable to this proposed data data
center in my opinion. It fails to
account for the unique risk and harm
associated with data centers. And what
happens when these facilities want to
expand outside of the footprint? Can you
make a commitment for an honest storm
water evaluation like was mentioned in
um by the mayor spokesperson in the LMP
article earlier today? If it's found
that it would negatively harm Lancaster,
can you truly say you would deny their
request to expand? I also have questions
about the Good Neighbor bargaining
agreement that was mentioned. Um what
kind of public input will we have on
that? um or is the mayor going to make
those uh negotiations unilaterally? Um
we deserve public input from the
beginning of this process, not after the
wool has already been pulled over our
eyes. Our community deserves better than
a huge fast-tracked energy eating
project that will affect our decade
affect our community for decades to
come. Thank you.
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. Harris. Our next speaker,
>> our next speaker is David Deise.
>> Good evening,
>> Dere. Thank you. Uh David Dere, 400
block of East Grant Street. Um a lot of
people said a lot of things better than
I could. They did a lot more research
than I had time to, but I'll just say
I'm here to ask you to put our community
ahead of outside business interests um
and to deny this in any way possible,
these data centers. Um the link between
environmental destruction is clear from
so many other examples that have already
been said today. They're going to use so
much power, massive amounts of energy,
which will accelerate climate collapse,
not just here, but everywhere around the
globe from all these data centers. Um,
terrible, terrible for the environment.
Um, and the harmful pollutants that they
also may cause are going to harm our
most vulnerable residents as well as
anybody else in the environ.
But I also want to say the AI industry
itself is the project of billionaires
who seek to cut cost by making our jobs
obsolete. We don't need to scab
ourselves. We don't need to let these
bureaucrats into our lives to run things
just because they have money. Um I don't
think we need to give them the tools to
take away our livelihoods while also
destroying our environment around us. We
have the choice to stop these things.
And we need to decide who we work for.
Uh do we work for these people just
because they have money they can come
into our community and destroy the
environment or do we have the option to
stop that from happening? Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Mr. Harris, our next speaker,
>> next speaker is Christine Kennedy.
>> My name is Christine Kennedy. I live at
10 North Market Street in downtown Lan
Lancaster.
And I appreciate the opportunity to
speak to the council and all of those
that have spoken so far
to Mayor Sarra, council president Bake,
city council members, and the
journalists that are in the house. I'm
writing to you and we'll forward this in
an email
in regards to the proposed air cooled
aspect of the data centers in Lancaster
City and their environmental impact. I
read in this morning's LMP paper as
others have said that the data centers
will initially be air cooled
mitigating concerns that were voiced
earlier about the water concerns.
I'm someone who has experienced the
noise pollution
impacts that data center fans firsthand.
I want to voice my concerns with the
hope that we can accelerate city policy
to address this in the future and as
much as we can with those facilities
that have already been approved.
Earlier this year, my husband and I
visited a family member who lives near
the data center that's featured in the
Time magazine article, "We're living in
a nightmare inside a health crisis of a
Texas Bitcoin town."
The article reveals the health impacts
to neighbors, animals, vegetation caused
by the constant noise from the fans that
cool the data center, including loss of
hearing, fainting spells, debilitating
vertigo, and nausea. The fans are heard
miles away. My cousin's home is 5 miles
away, and we can hear the fans there.
The recent LNP articles note that the
city classified a data center land use
as wholesale trade and storage. The
regulations related to that do not take
into account the unique impacts. As a
former urban planner, I turned to the
American Planning and Society
Association for Resources and found
zoning for data centers and
cryptocurrency mining. This article
addresses that impact for data centers
to look at noise as well as water and
uh power. I ask that you assure that the
city's noise ordinance covers and
controls this type of noise source so
that Lancaster City will not have the
same situation as Granbury, Texas. Thank
you.
>> Thank you.
Mr. Harris, our next speaker.
>> Next speaker is Rachel Krueger.
>> Thank you. Good evening.
>> Uh, thank you. Uh, Rachel Krueger. And
I'll admit that while I do live outside
of the city itself, I do live on
Greenfield Road about a half mile from
the proposed data center.
>> I appreciate you with providing me a
moment to discuss the proposed data
centers. to provide you a little bit of
background so you know where I'm coming
from. I hold a degree in geology and
have worked in the environmental field
for the last eight years. As others have
told you, AI data centers present a
number of environmental hazards. We're
seeing that now as more and more of
these facilities make national headlines
for churning out enormous amounts of
greenhouse gases and other compounds
inextricably linked to cancer and
cardiovascular and respiratory disease.
So, as another concerned citizen, I have
questions. Some you did touch on at the
beginning of the meeting, but I have a
few more concerns. For example, why an
AI data center? I understand that not
all land will meet all use criteria. I
understand that after years of
industrial use, the process of bringing
that land up to something like
residential use would be incredibly
costly. Red Rose Commons comes to mind.
That area is commercially developed
because it was previously occupied by
the aluminum industry. Redeveloping that
area to residential standards wasn't
feasible. So instead we made it
commercial and it created jobs and
brought revenue. I also have questions
like how will our energy infrastructure
be protected in other communities with
similar facilities? We have seen the
increased energy use by these data
centers get passed on to residents.
Should we expect to see our utility
bills increase? And what protections for
the environment and human health are
being considered? What thirdparty review
is being performed? And what if those
considerations aren't enough?
What happens when our community gets
sick? When our already heavily burdened
health care system is unable to keep up
with the increase in asthma and heart
disease and cancer? And what happens
with the lawsuit that follows? Because
as we all know, an emerging
environmental concern is a lawsuit on
the horizon. What then? And maybe these
questions have been considered. It
sounds like you have more information
than was originally presented to us. And
if that's the case, then great. But I
don't know because that information has
not yet been adequately communicated to
us. Now, I don't expect everyone to
become a tree hugging hippie. I don't
think that's realistic. But I ask that
we think of people like my grandma who
over the last decade of her life had
such severe asthma that she was unable
to get the mail at the end of her own
driveway. That is how bad Lancaster
County's air quality is.
I look forward to the forthcoming
information that you promised. And in
addition with the developer, I'd also
like to add that I'd like to meet with
the proposed tenants. I want to make
sure that they understand that by
building here, they have the same
obligation as you or I do to protect
this community. I yield my time.
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. Harris. Our next speaker,
>> next speaker is Anne Torres.
>> Good evening.
Hi. Oh, hi. My name is Anne Torres. I uh
live in Lettuce, but I work in
Lancaster. Years back, my friend had a
baby. Through IVF, they finally had
their baby. But over time, they noticed
that he was having issues breathing in
and out of hospitals, extensive stays,
but no answers. Just constant treatment
to keep him alive and breathing. And
it's heartbreaking to see a child who
was very healthy in every other way,
confined to a hospital bed for too much
of his life. I remembered the day she
came to me and said, "Anne will probably
need to move. He can't breathe here.
It's the air." As the move never came to
fruition, he saw more hospital visits
throughout his childhood. He is nine
now. He is relatively stable except for
the constant struggle of allergies and
asthma. If he gets sick like the common
cold, there's a good chance that he ends
up hospitalized. Is this the life the
future we want for our children?
Lancaster already ranks 22nd for the
worst air quality in the nation. Air
pollutants cause roughly 200,000
premature deaths yearly in the US. Now,
this should go without saying, but no
one should be dying from breathing the
air. the this these electricity
consuming fossil fueled power AI data
centers will accelerate that pollution
massively. In PA from 2024 to 2025,
there has been a 174% increase in
electric use due to these a AI AI data
data centers to the tune of9 billion.
A cost that is spread to you and me
because AI data centers whe while they
get to privatize their profits, they get
to socialize their operational costs. In
areas of high data center growth,
consumers can expect to see an an
additional estimated $450 added to their
yearly electric costs. Oh, and not only
do we help to pay to keep these centers
running, but these companies are getting
taxes tax exemptions in 36 states,
including PA. To qualify for these
exemptions, they must spend 75 million
on their investment property and
guarantee at least 25 jobs. 25 jobs.
What a low bar. An insult to the
community and trade for our health. This
exemption guarantees that they do not
have to pay sales tax on the very costly
vital tech equipment that they need to
build these centers. Which of course
means PA loses millions every time these
centers are built. Millions that could
go into healthcare, housing, and other
social safety nets that we are quickly
losing. In Indiana, an Amazon data
center promised to create 10,000 new
jobs. They failed to mention that 60% of
those jobs would be temporary
construction and the other 40% could
only be be fulfilled when they completed
their total project of 16 total data
centers. So, as AI data centers
steamroll this country, this state, this
county, quickly outpacing any regulation
in their industry, please ask yourself,
what are you, Shapiro, McCormick,
willing to trade for short-term monetary
investments? A child's future. This
cannot happen. Lancaster cannot let this
happen. Thank you.
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. Harris. for our next speaker.
>> Uh, next speaker is Frank Archelo.
>> Archolio.
>> Arolio.
>> Good evening, Mr. Arolio.
>> Hi. Thank you. Uh, Frank Archolio, Old
Trinity Place. It's only a circle, so
one block.
>> All the other speakers have dwelt on the
all the bad aspects of having a data
center. The gluttonous use of
electricity, the gluttonous use of
water, or if you're air cooling it, more
gluttonous use of electricity, and the
lack of jobs that eventually come out.
no matter what they promise. But I'm
going to ask the big Watergate question
today. What did you know and when did
you know it? We only found out on
Friday. But guess what? There was a $130
million
investment purchased in February. How
come we're just finding out about this
now?
The paper said when that investment was
made, it was made eyed for data centers.
Did you not notice?
You know, I've been in business and in
consulting for nearly 50 years. There is
no one that I've ever met who wants to
go spend $130 million
speculatively without knowing that that
investment was going to yield a return
without knowing that it was going to be
just okay with everyone to put a data
center here. And so we find out about it
on July 18th. None of you who found out
before that raised any qualms, talked to
anyone, talked to the public about what
it might do to us. And now, guess what?
We're told it's too late to do anything.
Oh, what a shame. If you had started in
February, we could have done a lot. Do
you think we wouldn't notice? Do you
think we wouldn't care? Do you think we
have to play cat and mouse with you to
check up on you to make sure that you're
doing your job? What we want is for you
to stop this damn data center right now.
We want control by the city over such
properties. They are not warehouses.
Trust me on that.
We need you to do the kinds of zoning
amendments that have been presented here
tonight that guarant and the regulations
need to guarantee water use, electricity
use, and to make sure that any other
environmental impact is dealt with not
by their asurances but by third-party
uh objective people.
Even Manor Township has this
Why can't Lancaster City?
I think somebody's been had. Either you
guys have been had or we've been had,
but it's not good for Lancaster County.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
Thank you. I want to thank the members
of the public for coming out tonight and
and speaking to council. Um,
as I mentioned before, this is new
information to many of us despite
insinuations. Um, and I want to also
assure you that council is committed to
keeping the public informed as updates
are provided on all matters, including
any public engagement opportunities
um that would be before this body or any
other opportunity to do so. So, thank
you very much uh for that. We will
proceed with the next item on our
meeting agenda this evening. I will, if
anyone needs to step out, give you a
moment to do so. Uh but otherwise, we
will keep going. And again, thank you
very much for your comments this
evening.
The next item on our agenda um is
reports requested by council. Uh that is
the capital budget public hearing and I
know that we'll uh have a presentation.
Members of council, you were sent a
presentation uh earlier this evening. So
that should be in your email. Uh, and we
have, I believe, directors Campbell, um,
and members of the public works team
that will be presenting,
and you can join us right here.
Mr. Harris confirming that the uh that
will be displayed on the screen
momentarily.
Working on it. Okay, great.
We'll take a brief pause as we work on
technology and get set up. Come on up,
>> council. While uh Council President, if
I may, while we're getting the
technology situated,
>> Mayor Sarra,
>> um I I want to just acknowledge the work
of the Department of Public Works in
preparing for council the first ever
capital plan uh to be presented. Uh this
is uh one of the requirements that was
born uh
The wireless mics are a little finicky.
We're
>> um we're trying.
>> Okay. So, as I was saying, uh this uh
capital uh plan um which uh Director
Campbell and his team are going to
discuss tonight, um is part of um is an
outcome of the adoption of the home rule
charter that requires uh council to uh
be presented on an annual basis the
capital plan uh um in its totality. And
so you will hear tonight uh related to
our um storm water, our our general fund
which includes our parks um active
transportation
um and roads as well as um our water and
sewer systems. Uh, and I'm really want
to just thank um, director Steve
Campbell uh, for his leadership in
bringing this across the finish line
along with members of his team. I also
want to give an acknowledgement uh to
David Capach uh for helping to translate
um all of the data into a new software
application that we are using that will
be able to provide the kind of
information that council needs to make
financial decisions as it relates to our
future investments in our capital
infrastructure. And with that, um turn
it back.
>> Thank you very much, Mayor Sarra. Uh,
Director Campbell team, good evening and
thank you for being here.
I'm Yes. And we're uh we'll just as we
learned at our last committee meeting,
we try to have one of those on at a
time. So, yeah. Thank you. Well, thank
you very much for the opportunity
to formally present the capital budget
in the form of the capital investment
program for fiscal years 2026 through
2030.
As per the home rule charter, we must
submit a capital budget annually by June
of each year, which we did on June 24th
of last month with a list of projects
published on June 30th.
In this presentation, we are reminding
you of the drivers of the capital budget
and we will be highlighting most of the
large projects within the budget. Our
esteemed deputy directors will present
their respective portfolios and you
should ask them any questions that come
to mind regarding the work in their
purview.
And as noted in the earlier
presentations, it is an opportunity for
you to clarify how you would like this
information presented in the future.
Director Tina Campbell will be available
to refresh and update you as to how we
establish estimated costs, etc. if
necessary and as you have questions.
Next slide, please.
In the aggregate, this is a graphic of
the 2026
to 2030 CIP over the next five years of
just over $300 million.
You'll note that the largest investments
are in water at 36% or 108 million,
wastewater at 31% or 94 million.
Both of those represent twothirds of the
CIP over the next five years. and Deputy
Director Christine Vulke Hilditch will
describe the drivers and the projects
that make up that portfolio of projects.
The remaining third is made up of
streets at 18% or $54 million and parks
and public works administration work
each at 5% at approximately $15.5
million each.
Deputy Director Cindy McCormack and uh
and I will present and describe th that
work.
The balance of that third is in storm
water just under 5% at approximately
13.6 million and deputy director Molly
Dagger will describe that work.
Next slide.
This just presents the work described by
enterprise fund where parks, streets and
public works administration comprise the
general fund. Storm water is its own
enterprise fund and water and wastewater
respectively are separate enterprise
funds.
Next slide.
We'll start with parks and streets. So,
I will turn it over to Deputy Director
of Public Right of Way and the city
engineer Cindy McCormack.
Thank you, Director Campbell. Um, if you
could go to the next slide, please. Um,
so these are our main um investment
drivers, I would say, related to uh the
public right of way. We have um and
these are these plans generally guide
the um investments that we're making in
each of these areas. So we have the
parks master plan which was um adopted
last year. This is identifying a lot of
our priorities related to renovating our
parks and any other um amenities or
services that the city may need related
to parks. Um we have our vision zero and
traffic safety plan. This is where we
are prioritizing
um traffic roadway improvements to um
the vision zero is that we have zero
fatal and serious injury crashes within
the city. So that is our goal and that's
what we strive towards. So that's making
sure that we're focusing our resources
on the most dangerous locations. Um then
we have our active transportation plan
and um this is identifying
um transportation facilities that
provide alternative modes of travel. So
rather than relying on the car to get
everywhere, we're trying to provide um
infrastructure for bicyclists,
pedestrians, other modes so that they
have options to feel safe when they're
traveling throughout the city. I would
say a lot of our projects we they sort
of overlap with the vision zero and
active transportation where we're trying
while we're providing that active
transportation we're also making sure
that we're improving safety for all
users. So not just the pedestrians and
bicyclists and then finally maintaining
our infrastructure. So, um you know, our
traffic signals, paving our streets,
those kind of improvements that need to
be made um to maintain that surface um
infrastructure.
Um and again, anytime that we're doing
any of those types of projects, we're
looking to see how we can improve safety
for the people using them.
So the um so yeah a lot of our
investment includes sort of baselines of
of making investments in each of these
areas but then also as additional
initiatives might come along they are
added as well.
Next slide.
So the first slide and I this is very
busy so I understand if we can't get
through necessarily all of it but um
we'll focus on our parks uh planning um
and these are ordered in the um amount
of investment. So the highest investment
is are located at the top but I may jump
around a little bit related to this. So
just from our parks master plan, you
know, we identified three parks that
were sort of the highest need um located
in the southeast. They were Joe Jackson
tot lot, the Ugants playground and
Southoun Park. So, um, we have been able
to prioritize those parks and, um,
actually Joe Jackson and Yul Gance have
just gone out, well, will be going out
to bid, I think tomorrow, um, as we have
completed the design for that and are
ready to, um, get that towards
construction. We're also working on
design related to the South End park as
well.
Um, and then just focusing on some
another the other project that's sort of
in construction or will be soon. Um if
you go down the list to the Knosoga
Pines connection, that is um a
connection where we're connecting the
Walnut Street fishing area to the
Knosogga Pines Park. So creating a path
uh between the two, crossing the river
and getting over to Konosoga Pines Park.
So um that is actually up to bid now as
well. So those are projects that are
currently or will be in construction
soon.
Um and then just sort of going through
identifying what our next priorities are
related to planning and um what parks
need to be improved next. We have
reservoir park which would you know
that's a very large park for us. So that
will require um planning and then um it
has a large um construction cost that
we're anticipating. Um and I guess this
is again this is just sort of an
estimate because we haven't really gone
through the whole process of what
exactly the scope of work will be but
given the size we anticipate it will be
a large project.
Um other planning uh projects include
we've talked about a municipal pool. Um
that's another area where um the pool
currently at Konosogga Pines Park is um
in starting to become in disrepair and
you know based on the location um we may
be looking we may want we want to look
at if there are alternative locations.
So that's one of the um areas where
we're starting to look at planning for
those. Other areas include the Duke
Street Mall, um the linear park, so that
50 foot wide park that travels along
South Duke Street. Um we're making
improvements along South Duke Street and
that project I'll talk about a little
bit later, but we're also wanting to
identify improvements for to make
activate the Duke Street Mall area as
well.
Um and then are there so then also we
have Colin Park um phase two which was
um a building that the city is currently
using that was a that was acquired
adjacent to Colin Park that the city is
currently using as a salt shed but that
future plans could include additional
park amenities uh there as well. So,
these are projects that we're looking at
um planning over the next five years,
starting the planning and even some
could potentially go to construction.
Um do we want to Yes.
>> No, I I'd like to just
I'd like to just make it clear what what
the columns are reading. Black on red is
a is a difficult visual and I apologize
for that. But the first five, the first
column, the column on the left is the
description of the project. The next
columns are fiscal 26, fiscal 27, fiscal
28, fiscal 29, and fiscal 30 culminating
in a total for the project, which is in
bold in almost in the middle of the
sheet. The next column is the column
that indicates what is already funded or
known to be funded.
The next column is what is anticipated
for the 2025 bond issue.
The the next column is the column of of
funds that have already been granted
towards these projects.
The next column is a column for other
sources of funding. They may not be
bond, may not be grants, they might be
something else a little bit different.
The the second to last column is the
2028 bond. So that's looking three years
out at an anticipated additional bond on
a three-year cycle. And last but
certainly not least is the column called
unfunded which recognizes that there may
still be work to be done to find the
funding for this project. And in
general, if we do not find that funding
in the time that it is needed, we will
do one of two or three things. We will
either look seek to see if that can be
added to the fiscal 20 the the 2028
bond.
We will look to possibly defer the
project or we will look to de uh to
descope or reduce the scope of that
project to stay within the funds and in
the budget we've got we already have.
That's the that's the sequence of the
columns that you'll see as you go
forward for all of these presentations.
Thank you for that, Director Campbell. I
appreciate it. A quick question that may
help provide context here. Um the grant
column are grants that we have we know
we have received only. Okay. And uh not
to say there won't be additional grants
uh in the future. And then I also want
to kind of put a fine point on the fact
that this is a plan that spans uh till
fiscal year 2030 and we're going to be
looking at it again every year. So these
columns will come up again and again and
again uh to benchmark and also update us
on changes, challenges, opportunities
every single year.
>> Absolutely. We're trying to build that
culture of knowledge of how to read this
kind of a capital budget. We're asking
if there's things that you need
presented in a slightly different way to
make it clearer for you, clearer for the
public to understand, but also to
recognize that you'll be seeing the same
things year after year, but we'll be
revisiting the entire program as time
moves forward.
>> Thank you. Um, I'll pause if counselors
have anything additional at this point
and we'll continue.
Thank you.
Okay, next slide then please. Thank you,
Director Campbell.
Um,
>> so this slide is highlighting um
basically what we're calling the streets
or the public rightway projects. As you
can see, there are many there. Um, and
again, this is identifying projects
related to vision zero, related to
active transportation, and then just
maintenance of our existing
infrastructure in general.
Um
and you know a lot of the projects that
we end up progressing are um ones that
we are able to find some matching grant
funds for. So um that that's often a
driver as to what we're trying to
progress are projects that we have a
high level of confidence that we would
be able to obtain grant funding. So
um I'll start at the top. We have our
safe streets for all um projects and
this is uh related to the uh federal
highway grant that we received um to
implement our vision zero plan. So um
the grant is worth uh $12.6 million with
a $15 million total. Um I will say that
some of these you know when I mentioned
the 12 um.6 6 million. This starts in
2026, so it's not accounting for funds
that have been expended in 2025.
Um
so we are, you know, these include some
supplemental studies like looking at the
conversion of um our one-way streets,
one-way streets to two-way. Um just
implementing um roadway improvement
projects on our high injury network. um
identifying improvements around schools
uh that um to help you know kids
traveling to and from school just to
improve the safety in those areas. Um we
are focusing on initially Carter McCrae
and the Mckesky campus. So um and then
just to give a plug too we have an open
house uh next um it's on the 30th I
believe that's next Thursday. Um that
will be our first open house related to
um vision zero and our safe streets for
all projects. So, it's going to be an
all day um drop in session at the
library. So, I encourage everyone to
come and stop and uh see in more detail
the work that we're doing on that
project.
Um next is our Water Street Bike
Boulevard project where we're adding um
have adding bike facilities, not adding
but using and making improvements along
Water Street from Harrisburg A to Fair
View uh for a bike boulevard. Um this
includes a couple off-road sections. Um,
and this is quite a large project, but
we do have um a large amount of grant
funding that is funding that project as
well. So, that should be happening uh
starting construction hopefully next
year. Uh, the next project is uh the
Northeast Greenway Walkway Boardwalk
Project. This is um a project connecting
the uh operation center at Riverside
Avenue to the Walnut Street Fishing Area
which would then connect to the Knesoga
um Pines Park connection that I just
spoke about earlier. So um that's
another project and again we have
significant grant funding related to
that project.
Um, and just to talk a couple about some
of the traffic we have quite a few
traffic signal um projects. We the the
state offers grant funding that allows
us to um take advantage of that almost
every year. So, we're wanting to make
sure that we're using that resource to
upgrade our traffic signals. Um there
are a couple other traffic signal
projects lo not noted on here which I
won't go into uh a lot of detail on but
um you can see them listed. Uh
Chesapeake and Broad uh bike facilities.
We're looking at adding uh bike
facilities on that uh stretch of roadway
from Queen Street all the way to King
Street. So that will be a significant
addition and we are fortunate enough to
have PendOt um will be paying for the
paving of that street. So that's another
um great opportunity there. Um and then
I will also highlight um Church Street
improvements and another project where
Pendot is assisting. We are looking we
will be taking away one lane of that
three-lane section to two lanes. Um and
then also making bike side path uh
improvements as well.
Um
and then there are also Ann and Juniata.
Ann is on our high injury network. Um,
so that is another project where we're
trying to improve safety around some of
the school campuses related to that. And
then, uh, I will jump to South Duke
Street. That is a project that will be
going to construction um, that has been
awarded to a contractor. So, that will
be starting construction this fall. Um,
and that is adding back in diagonal
parking along Duke Street and a side
path. So, I think I'm gonna
stop there unless anyone has any more
specific questions. I know there's a lot
of projects here.
>> Thank you. Uh just one quick question
regarding the grant funding. So, um
understanding that we're anticipating um
some of those funding opportunities, are
there any risks of losing that on some
based on some of the proposals at the
state right now?
I am not aware of any that we would be
at risk of losing at this point. You
know, um all the grants that are shown
there, we're under contract.
>> Okay.
>> Four. So, um I don't anticipate any
change there.
>> Great. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Council Amed.
>> Uh thank you, Council President. Uh
thank you, Council President, and thank
you. Uh this is very informative. Um, in
regards to some of the unfunded
allocations for, uh, multiple of the
projects, um, and kind of piggybacking
off councelor Royo's question, you know,
if we are not seeing those get funded
year-over-year, um, can we add that to
the 2028 bond like next year in the
projection? Um or I guess also as C uh
director uh Campbell mentioned like when
would we decide okay like we may need to
pause this project or defer this project
um if we don't see it move out of that
unfunded column.
>> Yeah I mean a lot of the projects we're
looking at um planning you know
initially so spending some money on
design so that we can sort of you know
we identify the scope and then pursuing
the funding. So, a lot of times we'll
start an initial design, but we won't
get into the final design until we have
that funding secured. Um, so it's sort
of, yeah, as Director Campbell
mentioned, we need need to evaluate it
year by year
>> and then, you know, and make sure that
that's still the priority and, you know,
how we want to move forward with it. Um
we also sometimes will look at how we
can reduce the scope um you know based
on a lot of times we'll get grant awards
that are less than what we ask for. So
we have to um adjust as
>> as more information becomes available to
us.
>> If I may add to that as well. This is
one of the advantages of having a
long-term capital plan. This is the
first time we've been able to look as
far as 30 to 32 years in advance. not as
a not as a guarantee that that's what
will happen on those particular years
but to anticipate when certain
infrastructure needs to be replaced when
certain infrastructure needs to be
upgraded or as technology changes etc.
It does allow, as Cindy had indicated,
we would be doing this assessment on an
annual basis to reconfirm the level of
funding that we have that's available
and and would reflect if anything has
changed, costs might rise, um
availability of materials may change.
All of that needs to be managed on on a
rolling basis. So this is gives us an
opportunity and you is an an opportunity
as well to see what the challenges are
and to help us make some of those
decisions.
>> Yes. Thank you. And you know I really do
appreciate this level of financial
planning. I I have a capital plan at the
hotel I manage. So you know it really
excites me to see that you know each
individual project has you know the
allocations year over year. So I really
appreciate you and your team's efforts
with that.
>> Thank you. Anything else from council
before we proceed?
Thank you.
>> Okay,
thank you. Uh, next slide, please.
And now we'll turn over to the
construction and operations
division which is under Matt Metsler who
was not able to join us this evening.
He's the deputy director of construction
and operations.
Um and we'll be describing the drivers
and projects within the public works
administ what we call the public works
administration portion. Next slide.
>> So the basic the basic investment
drivers include three bas
I don't know why but whenever the papers
are very close to these mics I I don't
know what sort of like Bluetooth
>> it's me
>> technology we're working with here but
>> I'm just
>> that's okay. Maybe it's you. It's your
electric personality.
Thank you.
>> Um, so there for for the the next five
years or so, these are the key drivers
for us. The first two are drivers not
just for these next five years but
ongoing um facilities and maintenance
operations and efficiency and the
welcome center renovation which I'll
talk about a little bit more in terms of
maintaining our parks and public
property. We have 26 public parks and
recreational areas, five waiting pools,
one full-size pool, eight major
operational facilities, 10 public
restrooms, and we plan and replace a
plan and replacement schedule based on
our facilities condition assessment that
we put in place back in 2022 where we
were able to do a facility condition
assessment of all of our built
uh what we call our V vertical
construction including the parks.
We're looking for opportunities for
operational in efficiencies as well,
which includes combining smaller
satellite offices and operations into
centralized locations
for efficiency, economics of scale,
public convenience, and reduction in
time and fuel. and combining similar
functions across bureaus and departments
under one roof, such as archiving,
equipment storage, vehicle storage and
maintenance, warehousing, and expanding
capabilities and reducing costs. and
certainly one jewel in the crown of
Lancaster city assets, the welcome
center renovation,
the centralized hub for implementing key
goals identified in the tourism master
plan and implementing technology and
focused advertising on realizing
Lancaster as a tourist destination.
Next slide.
So, similar to what Cindy had done, I
I'll be going through several of the
larger projects related to public works
administration,
construction and operations. The first
one on this on this sheet is the
operation center, what we're calling the
operations center expansion. It's
consolidation of functions including
equipment storage, warehousing,
archives, etc. At this particular
moment, we don't have the ideal location
for such, but we recognize that we have
facilities scattered throughout the
city, and that makes us significantly
less efficient and makes it difficult to
maintain certain of our equipment. So,
we are looking looking at uh
opportunities to consolidate. If we do
not find the type of site that we're
looking for, there actually is a space
on part of one of our existing sites
that might be able to accommodate part
of that work.
The next is the capital projects.
The next is capital projects outlays for
facility condition assessments. As I had
indicated, the 2022 FI facility
condition assessments gives an
exhausting an exhaustive list of the
assets, whether they're windows, doors,
foundations, roofs, um, equipment,
appliances, and things like that that
need that have rem uh that indicate the
remaining useful life of those
particular assets. Allow us to more
predictively and more accurately
determine what needs to be replaced and
when it needs to be replaced. and the
relative costs for that. In the past, I
think we've done a very very good job of
identifying or anticipating what the
needs were, but it was not based on
a lot of science, if you will. We would
walk each of the facilities and say, "We
have eight eight of the 20 eight of the
40 buildings windows are broken. It's
time to replace the windows." rather
than perhaps being able to do the
calculus that says it's going to be less
expensive to replace those eight windows
right now and wait until the remaining
use for life later. So we are in the
very enviable enviable position that
many of our facilities are in very good
shape.
And it also means we have we now have
the tools to more accurately and more
judiciously spend rather than spend
because we fear that something may fail.
The next is on-site solar generation.
Currently unfunded to identify and
implement solar on the roofs of sites or
existing city buildings. We currently
spend approximately up approaching $3
million annually on costs for power and
electric almost 20% of which could be
generated by solar and thus see a return
in as little as eight years. This also
goes towards our climate action plan
efforts. So part of the goal would be to
work with with solar and energy brokers
and Molly may be able to speak to a
little a little bit more on how to uh
utilize the roofs of buildings that are
structurally appropriate for such to add
solar and therefore reduce our our
energy costs.
the salt shed. Cindy had mentioned that
we need to be able to consolidate a
single location for efficiency and
convenience, saving precious moments in
snow removal, but also releasing for
other more public uses the site and
sites that we currently use for salt
storage.
The welcome center renovation, and I I I
neglected to indicate, but you can see
the numbers up above. The operation
center we're gueststimating will be
approximately 6
9 million over the course of several
years. Um the capital projects outlay,
we're looking at approximately $750,000
annually to look at the work that needs
to be re revisited from the facility
condition assessment that may increase
and drop depending on the uh the the
remaining useful life of certain of the
assets. The on-site solar generation, we
estimate for the roofs that we believe
we can do this on, approximately $2.5
million.
The salt shed approximately $1.5
million. And then the welcome center
renovation approximately $1.5 million.
Built in the late n 1790s, it was built
as a public office house and likely the
original city hall. The building now
serves as Lancaster's city's welcome
center and will be upgraded and restored
to implement key goals identified in the
tourism master plan, including offices,
meeting spaces, and display and
storytelling.
Two other areas where we need specific
work are the Lancaster Police Station
roof needs to be replaced. That building
is more than 20 years about 20 years old
now. I forget exactly how old, but it is
it is the roof has reached the end of
its of its design useful life and so it
needs to be replaced. And then last but
certainly not least in this particular
stretch, the citywide telephone platform
replacement. Oh, not sorry, it's not
last. citywide telephone platform
replacement in aid of upgrading our
telephone system at $184,000 or about
$64,000 $62,000 per year for that
upgrade.
City Hall facade cleaning and ceiling at
to the tune of $50,000 of the building
we are we are sitting in right now. The
facade requires cleaning, some modest
repair and sealing to better preserve
the the exterior of the the and
therefore make it less expensive to
maintain. And certainly last but
certainly not least, for many who are
inhabit the building, the recycling
center at uh 850 New Holland Avenue
where it needs a new boiler, the people
who are serving us to deal with our
recycling are freezing their blanks off
because of the inadequacy of the
existing um system.
Next slide.
So just in quick summary, this
summarizes the subsets of the general
front fund CIP.
Note that about 64 million of the $85
million is funded, which leaves about 20
million
20 almost 21 million unfunded. More than
50% of the general fund CIP is from
grants and other sources. We anticipate
4.2 2 million input from the 2028 bond.
And otherwise, we will continue, as we
had mentioned before, to seek grants for
the balance. And where not successful,
we will either look to increase the ask
from the 2028 bond or reduce scope for
these otherwise necessary investments or
in an even worst case scenario, defer
those those projects.
Uh before going into storm water which
is the next the next um enter enterprise
fund are there any questions regarding u
either construction and operations or
anything within the g within the general
fund?
>> Thank you director Campbell counselors
anything before the next section
>> thank you continue. Okay. So, I will now
let's turn to the stormwater CIP which
deputy director Molly Dagger will
outline for us. Molly,
sorry everybody. Can you switch? Just
don't leave that one off. Yep. We've
angered the Bluetooth microphone gods.
Don't use that one. And Cindy, don't
forget. Just push it away. Let's try
that one now.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. All right.
>> Sorry about that, everybody.
>> Even more electric, I think.
>> Even more electric.
>> Thank you, Director Campbell. Uh, next
slide, please.
We'll show the pretty rain garden for a
moment and then we can advance to the
next slide. Great.
So, the city's five-year capital plan
that I present to you this evening for
the stormwater fund prioritizes
strategic investments that deliver
multiple benefits environmental,
economic, and communitywide.
Lancaster is a national leader in green
infrastructure, using our rain gardens,
our tree trenches, our green roofs, our
permeable pavements to manage storm
water. This is well embedded in our
long-term planning and I'll go through
some examples of that on the next slide.
But this is transforming how we manage
water in a way that also serves our
climate resilience goals and our
neighborhood revitalization.
So these practices are reducing
flooding, improving water quality, air
quality, supporting our pollinators,
cooling our neighborhoods, and making
our city more beautiful and livable.
We've been doing green infrastructure
for so long here in Lancaster that while
many of our systems are performing as
designed or overperforming, it is time
for us to be planning strategically
for the uh as part of the long-term
operation and maintenance to be
allocating some of our capital funds to
more substantial corrective actions to
some of our assets to ensure the
continued long-term success.
We've built a strong track record. Our
projects are strategically implemented
to reduce combined sewer overflows that
I'm sure Christine will touch on later
uh via our long-term control plan and
also to meet the state permitting
requirements in our non-combined parts
of the city known as the municipal
separate storm sewer system or the MS4
areas.
Uh next slide please.
similar format. The first half of the uh
slide that you see shows the different
allocations from 2026 through 2030 and
then some some of the funding mechanisms
on the right hand side. Uh with respect
to some of those regulatory uh um
obligations that I mentioned before, um
I'm going to jump around a little bit.
Uh these are again in order in which uh
from largest to to smallest but I wanted
to just on the long-term control plan
and on our MS4 obligations highlight
first the ARI projects that you see
that's the asset renewal inventory
projects. Uh this is an acronym that
we're using in our long-term control
planning. Uh but this is these are
basically the green infrastructure
projects that the city is committed to
in our combined sewer system areas. Um
planning efforts in 2028 will dictate
what those are and what those will be
because as you'll see a lot of our
initiatives are um uh combined with
other city initiatives as well. So that
ARRI project is directly for those
combined sewer system areas. Likewise,
the MS4 collection system upgrades,
that's those are the separate sewer
system areas. This could be new uh
inlets or new piping uh to alleviate
flooding and to improve uh roadway
conditions and safety improvements. This
could also be green infrastructure such
as the improvements that were made at
Longs Park uh in order to meet those
permitting obligations as well.
Uh, one of the most important things
that I wanted to show though is uh, one
of the most one of the city's most
effective strategies is bundling these
storm water improvements with other
capital improvements. So, you'll notice
a common thread through the list. The
Stormwater Bureau looks at green
infrastructure potential in the paving
plan, the city's vision zero and safe
streets for all initiatives, which is
why you'll see uh things like reservoir
park uh in the stormwater CIP as well.
Um just a note, there is going to be
green infrastructure at Joe Jackson, Ule
Gans, and South End. Um the parks that
Cindy highlighted earlier. Um and and so
we do we strategically incorporate green
infrastructure and uh as many of these
projects as possible. Um other
collaborative efforts that you see on
this list include the storm water costs
for capital improvements. Uh they might
not be green infrastructure but they
will have important storm water benefit
and again alleviating flooding,
improving um conditions in our in our
streets and um in our community. uh the
operations center facility storm water
contribution. There will be some storm
water improvements that happens through
those uh consolidated uh and and
expansion opportunities that Steve
touched on as well as green
infrastructure at the new Bay Street
community garden uh which will we hope
to begin planning next year uh with
implementation as early as 2027.
So this integrated appro approach
stretches every dollar load lowers total
project costs and minimizes disruption
to residents when we can be tackling
certain construction or multiple
construction efforts at the same time.
So thanks for bearing with me. I know
I'm bouncing around a lot. The only two
items that I hadn't specifically
mentioned on this list are the
corrective actions, the uh green
infrastructure corrective actions. And
that's what I had alluded to before.
where we are putting sort of a slightly
increased placeholder um in future years
to account for the fact that as we grow
our green infrastructure program and as
these systems age, we do want to be
allocating funding uh for the renewal of
those green infrastructure assets that
we have. Uh and then last but certainly
not least is the trees for people
implementation uh which will use a
combination of federal funds and the
2022 storm water bond funding for the
urban forest reset. This is under
construction right now around our city
streets. Um and will continue on uh in
through the next few years. Um we
presented a little bit about the urban
forestry program to council earlier this
year. But again, we're creating a
healthier, more robust uh tree canopy
along the city streets. This tackles a
number of storm water related goals. We
think that trees are the city's best
green infrastructure as well as other
climate climate resiliency goals as
well.
So over the next five years, residents
will see projects in more parks, more
neighborhoods, and more public spaces.
Uh and again to manage storm water, and
to uh to improve our daily life through
those other benefits that I had
mentioned
>> before we
Oh, sure. Sure. Yes. Questions about
storm water projects.
>> I do have a question. uh the lines for
the MS4 collection system and the
um
there's another line I'm sorry and the
uh OSA the green infrastructure corre
corrective action yes
>> um actually no just the MS4 system line
so that's the same number repeated
year-over-year I'm assuming there was
some assumptions made about just like
average cost can you talk a little bit
more about what those could
And then also I see it's in the n the
unfunded category. Can you talk a little
bit more about that?
>> Yes. Um there were some assumptions made
and it this is um a combination of um
uh upgrades that we might need to make
in our separate uh sewer areas. These uh
this is a placeholder because we don't
know yet what those might be. Um the
other thing the other sort of big
placeholder um and the reason that it's
unfunded is because uh the city is
actually in compliance and has met all
of its current MS4 permit uh project
requirements. It was called a pollutant
reduction plan and the city has
fulfilled those obligations. the state
um is revising the permit requirements
for the MS4 permit, but it has
administratively extended the permit uh
for at least another 12 months. And we
we do not know yet what the permit
obligations will be.
So, we don't know yet what we will spend
or what or where we will target those
funds yet. Um
>> exactly when.
>> Yeah. Or exactly when. And so what we've
done is is made an educated guess based
on the money that was spent in the last
permit cycle. Um and we were very
successful uh with grant funding um and
u other types of of funds, penvest
loans, things like that for some of
those projects. So we are confident that
once we know what those permit
obligations will be, we can be updating
those uh numbers and hopefully have much
less in the unfunded category to present
to council next year.
>> That makes sense that we will be able to
match them with funding sources as we
get a little bit more defined. Y
>> thank you.
>> Uh councilors, anything on this one
before we proceed? Councelor Hirs.
>> Thank you. Council President, just had a
brief question on the trees for people
program. Um, and I understand that
that's going forward over the next
couple years into 2028. Can you just
reiterate what the what the goal is as
far as like number of trees planted over
the next three years and then um if you
happen to have it available um what
progress has been made thus far on said
goals.
>> Sure. Um
I'm trying to do some fast math in my
head here. Uh, I know that through a
half a million dollars in ARPA funding
that the city received through the
Lancaster Clean Water Partners, we are
installing about 380 new street trees
this year. Uh, we are I think we're
about halfway through that target. So,
uh, probably a little under 200 trees
were planted uh, in the spring and then
the rest will be fall planting. there's
some concrete work associated uh with
that project happening now. Um
so that will wrap up by the end of this
year. And then uh with the other um with
the other federal funds that we received
from the US Forest Service, we are
targeting about
we're still finalizing the numbers. We
were looking at trying to find upwards
of 400 new street tree wells around the
city and then either uh conducting
restorative pruning to bring trees that
were in fair condition back up to an
acceptable level of of health uh tree
health. Um and then where that wasn't
appropriate removing and replacing uh
trees as part of that effort. So that
could be another upwards of of
two to 300 new trees through that effort
as well. So it would be 450 plus 380
plus two to 300 more.
>> Thank you. It's very exciting.
>> Yeah.
Counselors, anything additional on this
slide?
>> Thank you.
So far so good.
>> That was the okay one. Okay.
>> Um, next we're going to turn to
utilities enterprise funds will be which
will be outlined by deputy director of
both wastewater and water utilities
Christine Vulke Hilditch.
>> Good evening.
>> Next slide please.
So, we're going to start with the
wastewater treatment plant. Our plant's
located off New Danville Pike, right
outside the city. It has a capacity of
32 million gallons a day. Um, on a good
day, dry weather, we may be running
about 18 million gallons a day. When it
rains, our flows go up to 50 million
gallons a day. So, we can see by the
picture, there's a lot of facilities,
there's a lot of components.
In addition to the plant, we also have
seven pump stations that pump waste
water to the plant. Waste water also
comes in through gravity to this to the
plant. And we also maintain over
hundreds of force mane and gravity sore
within the system. So when we go through
our capital plan, you can see that it's
a significant investment to treat water.
And on this end, we're treating we're
reclaiming waste water and putting it
back into the Konosoga River.
Next slide.
So, our drivers are our infrastructure
and regulatory requirements.
As you've heard over the years, we have
a judicial consent decree with the EPA
and the D to address our combined sewer
overflows. and were required to develop
a long-term control plan. We've
submitted an alternatives analysis
and our next regulatory requirement is
in September to submit the long-term
control plan.
The regulatory drivers in wastewater are
significant. We are now being regulated
with a new NPDES permit, which is the
permit that allows us to discharge into
the Konos Stoa River that has additional
requirements.
Most important is the start of
monitoring for the forever chemicals.
You've heard a lot about those in the
news and we'll be talking a little bit
more about them in our water system.
So when we talk about not knowing what
the future holds and that we will be
revising this capital plan
year-over-year,
our regulatory drivers will be what
affects us.
In Pennsylvania, we are still allowed to
land apply the solids generated in the
wastewater treatment process. We do this
also under permit and in several states
throughout the nation that practice is
being eliminated.
So our concern as a driver for the
future is that we generate less
bioolids.
We are looking at significant
infrastructure spending for digestion,
anorobic digestion, which will allow us
to both reduce the amount of solids that
we have to dispose of as well as give us
opportunities in energy generation.
Um, one of the things that the current
federal regulations allow is the ability
to generate credits
um for for developing green gas. An
anorobic digtor generates methane and
that methane can be reused
um on the grid on the on the gas grid.
So, we're trying to position ourselves
for less expenses. Although debt will
increase, we'll be looking at less costs
for disposal. Over the past 10 years,
we've seen our disposal costs uh double.
You know, we're we're over $2 million
now for disposal costs for for sludge.
Next slide, please.
Within our capital projects, we have
funding for what we call our municipal
partners.
So the plant takes in waste water from
the Lancaster area sewer authority from
the suburban
area sewer authority
from
missing one Leola
as well as East Lampider uh sewer
authority. So several other municipal
partners contribute to capital projects
at the wastewater plant as well as the
stations the pump stations. So depending
on the use in terms of their flow
contribution will drive how much they
contribute to the capital projects. So
in our
um in our project information we have um
what the city will be uh spending as
well as um some of these will be
contributed by other funding sources.
We'll start with anorobic digestion,
which is to install dryers and uh tanks
that will um reduce the amount of sludge
that we generate.
Our next project is a secondary
clarifier. Clarifiers
settle the solids that are generated in
the process. We'll be adding a sixth
clarifier for additional treatment
capacity and resiliency.
The next project is the in is the
rehabilitation
of an interceptor um from the that feeds
the knot gardens pumping station.
Following that is the water street sewer
separation project. will be separating a
combined sewer system which will help
reduce our combined sewer overflows.
We're adding a scrubber in our
chlorination facilities. This is for
safety and resiliency so that we can
address um any issues with chlorine.
The north primary clarifier
rehabilitation
is for new equipment within those tanks,
new flights, scrapers
um that will help settle the sludge.
South screening headworks is uh for new
screens. Um these screen the waste water
as it comes into the plant.
The collection systems improvement is a
placeholder for any issues that occur
within the collection system and we'll
see this as a placeholder
year-over-year.
This project um allows us to line and
replace uh gravity sores within the
system.
The south primary clarifier
rehabilitation very similar to the north
project we are replacing equipment
within the tanks rehabilitating the
concrete um as part of that project.
Broad Street is another source
separation project.
Um, next slide, I'm sorry.
So, on the second page, um, we have
structural repair and piping system
upgrades. some of our piping and the
plant property is um from the 1930s,
1980s.
So, we'll be looking at replacing key um
pipes. We've had some leaks over the
years. So, this is um a general
rehabilitation project of all the
piping.
Our motor control center replacement is
in the control building. We'll be um
replacing switch gear within that
building.
The North Palm Station Cso outfall
project is to rehabilitate the Clay
Street outfall. This is up near the Macy
um campus. The sort the system is about
100 years old. So, we'll be structurally
reinforcing the the sore outfall and the
piping that that leads to that outfall.
Um the south train diversion is for
chlorination improvements on our cso
outfall 100 our combined uh outfall.
We are rebuilding uh four belt filter
presses and two discharge conveyors.
This is in our solids processing and uh
the presses dewater the sludge and the
conveyors take it out to the trucks for
disposal.
The chlorine contact upgrade is for
structural repairs in our chlorine
contact tanks.
The next project is site paving. We have
a significant large site and we're we're
repaving it. And the last one is um the
lime stabilization is to replace a the u
bio bofilters um odor control system
media.
Thank you.
>> So that's a lot of projects. It
>> is
>> over five years um mainly because of the
infrastructure. So one of our drivers as
I said is the regulatory requirements.
You will note in this particular list of
projects we do not have major um
long-term control plan projects. That is
because our strategy when we're putting
in our alternative analysis is to
concentrate on infrastructure and
wastewater and more importantly the
drivers in water. So we'll be spending a
lot of money on water. We know this is
bad but water is is even more because of
the regulatory drivers. So we are going
to propose to the EPA that we will first
spend money in the water system for
compliance and we will not start
spending on the csos other than some of
the source separation projects and the
GI projects that Molly mentioned but the
the the rest of the spending would be
out in probably 2037. We're spending 10
years spending in water and then we'll
start spending in sewer other than what
we're talking about as the the normal
repair and replacement of the
infrastructure.
>> Thank you. Um before we proceed, I have
two questions. Uh the first is the
impacts of those separation projects,
water street sewer separation and then
there was uh there was others there
overall what is the impact of those
projects? I know you mentioned focusing
on the water first, but is that a
significant or an insignificant impact?
If you could kind of just talk about it
in general terms,
>> I'm going to refer that to to Molly
because she's going to be managing the
project, but Sur is going to be paying
for it.
>> Okay,
>> great. Thank you.
>> Yes. So, the Water Street sewer
separation will be built ahead of the
Water Street Bike Boulevard project that
Cindy spoke about. these uh this will
remove approximately 40 acres of
imperous drainage that is today going
into the Angleside
>> sewer shed which is the city's largest
um combined sewer system. Um, and at a
relatively costefficient manner,
projected costs are about I just looked
at this yesterday, 250,000 per acre,
which is a little bit less than what our
green infrastructure costs. Again, we
are there are some efficiencies
efficiencies in the fact that we're
collaborating with other users and that
there was a a portion along Fair View
that was separated um several dec
decades ago but was just then tied back
into the combined sewer system. So,
we'll be uh disconnecting that. uh Broad
Street uh is uh less. It's about nine
acres, but then we will have the
opportunity to disconnect from the north
basin and uh into infrastructure that
the city actually already built under
the Wickers Sham turf fields under the
Macy campus. Yes. And then we'll have
the opportunity to daylight that storm
water into Gra's Run, which the city
invested in a stream restoration project
a number of years ago. So it will bring
back some base flow and we're already
collaborating with the school district
uh to incorporate some environmental
opportunities there as well. Great.
Thank you for that context. That's
exactly the kind kind of connection I
was hoping to make with that question.
And then my second question is um the
last line on the first uh slide, the
last one on the list, annual escrow
special and emergency uh improvements.
So obviously we have to put something
aside and plan for rainy days. No pun
intended, rainy days. Um, lots of rainy
days. Rainy days in terms of like when
things happen that we don't plan for.
Has this number that we we've chosen
half a million dollars annually. Does
that generally line up with about how
much we typically spend on these sort of
like emergency improvements that come
up?
>> No.
>> Okay.
>> Um,
>> it it is a placeholder. Okay. Um, we
contribute um little less than 250,000
and so do the partners.
>> Okay. We put it in escrow and we tap it
as needed. So it may be a small planned
project like we buy a new mixer in the
aeration system, a small roof repair or
it may be because something broke.
>> Okay.
>> So it is a placeholder. Um we've been
doing it for the last maybe eight years.
It's been working pretty well. Sometimes
we even defer like you know every year
but maybe it's every 14 months or maybe
we have to um fund every eight months
but we we fund it we plan for it on a
frequency of an annual contribution.
>> Thank you for that and I appreciate the
good stewardship of our systems. Any
additional questions from council on
these two slides?
Thank you. Oh, I'm sorry. Councelor
Clest.
>> Thank you, Madam President, and thank
you for the presentation.
And I'm not sure who would answer this
question. And
how is the department working to
minimize the cost of those projects?
>> We comp we competitively bid all of our
projects. Um we always ask the engineers
to do a cost estimate so we can
determine whether we are in budget um
you know from estimates we might have
done with um
you know during the design process. So
our biggest driver is competitive
bidding so that you're you're putting
together a good plan set of plans and
specifications that you can put out. Um
we do our bidding on the platform called
pen bid so it's widely advertised. um
within the state. So I think the most
important thing is to have good plans
and specifications so that your
contractors know exactly what you want
and you minimize your change or for any
unforeseen circumstances.
>> Thank you. Thank you, Madam President.
>> Thank you,
>> Council Royal.
>> Maybe this question is too soon for
tonight. Um but curious about capacity
and project management for a lot of
these projects. Um there's a lot going
on especially in 26 and 27. Uh what does
capacity look like on the teams as well
as what does project management look
like in sequencing these projects? Um
just kind of thinking about
construction, thinking about resident
experience. Um how does that play a
factor into some of these uh some of the
timeline for for a lot of these
projects?
When we look at um you know in terms of
internal external capacity our design
work is done with outside engineers
managed with inside engineers.
The largest project will be the
digesttor project and the phasing of
that will also be looked at as what our
as our debt you know changes um because
that'll be a significant borrowing. Um
we will be at least two years plus in
design and probably three to four years
in construction. So it'll be a steady
u project that will go on long term. the
clarifier. I thought we'd already be
under design. We had had some funding
set aside in previous bond funds and
ended up reconfiguring projects because
of the time it's taking to buy the land.
We have to buy a little sliver of land
from PPNL to put the clarifier in the
northern part of the plant. Um that has
taken significant time. they're now in
PUC approval for selling that little
piece of land to us as another municipal
entity and then we have to go through a
land development process with um
Lancaster Township. So, I'm a little
concerned on when we actually can start
um more right now than than the capacity
issue. Mainly because a lot of our
projects on this are at the plant. So,
our in-house engineer can keep an eye on
them, but we'll also have inspections
inspectors uh from the consulting,
you know, out I'm sorry, we will have
inspectors uh from the consulting
engineer um who will help manage the
day-to-day. So we do have and we do
access outside help.
On a slightly different note, I think it
is impressive just yeah the amount of
projects that you're being uh uh that
are being discussed this evening. Um you
know we do have a lot of expertise
within DPW and and city staff. I also am
very um pleased with the collaboration
that happens between uh divisions in the
city as well. I know, you know, we have
a lot of projects that are either out to
bid or going out to construction and
there's a lot of expertise in all three
division in all four divisions, but when
when we're looking at a storm water
project, we rely on one of the public
works engineers who is an expert in
procurement. Um, and we will rely on a
wastewater uh project manager, you know,
on some of these sewer separation
projects. And so we really do um I think
uh work well together to sort of lighten
the load a bit. Um and we are all busy.
And if I could just add one last thing,
um we do on an annual basis in the in
the operations budget budget for the
staff. We don't always fill fill or
fulfill all those all those vacancies or
all the needs that are that are required
to fulfill the work. But that that's why
we have some flexibility to work with
outside contractors and outside
consultants as well. If if suddenly we
get um oversight agencies that are quick
in their review and get things done a
bit faster, that generally means we can
accelerate or move a project forward
faster. But that also means we need to
calculate do we have the staff
internally to manage that work. Do we go
outside to to do that work or or not.
Rarely is that the case. Although there
have been several cases in especially in
in wastewater in the last couple of
years where things have gotten
accelerated. But similarly there are
things that get delayed.
>> Thank you.
>> All right we can continue. Thank you.
>> So now I'd like to talk about our water
system.
Our water system has two plants, one on
the Konos Stoga River and one on the S
Saskuana River. Combined, they can
produce 36 million gallons of water a
day.
We also have one reservoir, Oyster
Point,
five water tanks,
and four pump stations, as well as
hundreds of miles of pipe underground.
We serve over,
excuse me, we serve over 120,000 people
within the city and the surrounding
municipalities.
Our investment drivers in water are
replacing our aging infrastructure.
We've been producing water since the
late 1800s at the Konosoga site. Now
granted, we don't have the same plant,
but that's how long we've been producing
water. Our Susuana plant was built in
the 1950s.
So when you start thinking about it, all
of a sudden that's 80 years ago. So we
have um what we'll talk about tonight is
some of our larger projects which is to
replace transmission lanes lines that
are now 80 years old. And you don't
think about how you know how long we've
been producing water in the city.
But water right now is facing
many state and federal regulations.
Most recently, we had the improved lead
and copper rule. And they did call it
that, the improved lead and copper rule.
What the improvement was is that we had
to replace all lead service lines within
10 years. The first regulation that came
out
required it in 30 years. So, our
timelines for work have significantly
uh decreased.
We did a inventory,
initial inventory that we submitted last
year. We have a new inventory due in
October of 2027.
And then all those lines have to be
replaced by 2037.
And certainly, you've seen us all over
the website in in media, you know,
asking our water customers to please
identify their service line in their
homes.
So those efforts will continue.
The other significant regulatory red
driver is the maximum contaminant
levels. We call these MCLs for POS and
POA. And those are the forever
chemicals.
They were passed in January 14th of
2023.
It's required quarterly monitoring at
the entry points of our water into the
system at both treatment plants. We've
been very successful in our monitoring
efforts on the Suscuana River or excuse
me the Suscuana plant which takes water
from the Suscuana River. We've been well
under these MCLs.
However, as we saw the effects of the
drought over the past year,
we saw the levels of POA increase at the
Kn in the Knosoga River for customers
served by the Konesoga plant.
These are significant regulatory
drivers. We've been uh told by the PA
that they expect us, you know, to be in
compliance.
We haven't negotiated any
consent decrees or agreements at this
point in time. We've just been at put on
notice. Um but we are planning for um
long-term compliance
because on the federal level they have
published even more stringent
regulations at four parts per trillion
and these will be effective in April of
2029.
So we have two drivers here on the state
level, a requirement that's in effect
now and one on the federal level in
2029.
There's certainly been a lot in the news
about the concern of Forever Chemicals.
Our monitoring and planning continues
to achieve compliance with these
standards.
And it's put water companies throughout
the nation at a disadvantage where we're
treating for a contaminant that we never
created.
It's not naturally occurring. It was a
man-made chemical and now um we're all
forced to address it accordingly with
regulations.
Another significant driver has been the
drought and water withdrawal.
The city is regulated by the by the D in
Pennsylvania
on how much it can withdraw from the
Knosuga River.
And over the next 25 years, they expect
us to withdraw less. So that as climate
change occurs and there are droughts
from time to time, we will be
constrained by how much water we can
pull out of the river. So we're looking
at long-term planning to address that,
too.
So now I'd like to get into the
projects.
Next slide please.
Our first two projects are to replace
those 1950 error transmission lanes from
the Suscuana plant. We're looking at
phase two, the line that runs from the
Suscuana treatment plant to the Oyster
Point reservoir.
And phase three is the raw water
transmission main from the intake on the
Susuana River to the treatment plant. So
these two projects um
we've um we're in right now permitting
with D and we do expect to go out to bid
um late in the year early next year um
pending approval of our uh PENvest loan.
We do expect to go uh seek Penvest
financing for these two particular
projects.
Our next project is the lead service
line. Um this particular project will
not be spent all at once. We'll have a
series of um
small smaller projects as we submit for
funding um to the Penvest Authority.
We've recently been successful on a um a
small project in the city of aboutund
and some hundred lines um where we did
get part grant funding and part uh loan
funding. So we'll be doing similar
investments over the next couple years.
Our next project is the South Pump
Station which will start later in 2028.
This station will help feed the new
South
tank.
The next are the lead service line um
improvements um near-term when this was
ranked um highest to lowest. That's why
the the two projects um kind of um
separated.
Um the next project is the intake
for the Suscuana low service pump
station. This screens the water as it
comes into um the pump station and then
it's pumped to the plant.
We have placeholders for um replacement
of transite water pipe within the
distribution system.
The next is water quality improvements
um at Lafayette tank which also are
driven by water quality regulations.
The next is a placeholder for cleaning
and lining pipes in the distribution
system.
The next is handling solids at the
knogga plant
to improve um our our treatment system.
The next is at the Konosogga plant uh
rehabbing the tanks that are in the
treatment system. They're the rapid mix
and the equalization tanks.
Next slide, please.
This project is replacement of the large
cast iron manes that are near the water
plant. These are big distribution mains.
This is a design of the PAS compliance.
Um our preliminary um
solution is that we will be looking at
um taking water from the Suscuana River
instead of the Knosoga River. will be
basically putting in another line, a set
of lines to bring water into the plant.
The next is the knosogga membrane
replacement.
The cast iron pipe and materials are for
city crews for for self-performance of
work in within the city.
The knosogga clear well coating
replacement is next.
The other two are to replace. The next
one is vectors for transmission and
distribution. This is for our crews in
the performance of their duties.
The Susuana water treatment plant clear
well relining very similar to the
Konosoga. The clear wells are what hold
the finished water. They are anywhere
from
80 years old
to 100 years old in age. So we'll be um
doing a major project of um
rehabilitating the concrete and then
coating that concrete.
This will extend the life of the the
tanks.
The next is replacing electrical
equipment at the Konos Stoa water
treatment plant.
The next one is a placeholder for lead
service line customer reimbursements.
We are required
under the Pennsylvania public utilities,
the PUC,
um to
replace lead lines on either side of the
of the service lateral, not only what
the city owns, but what the customer
owns. And this is a placeholder for
leadline replacements that customers had
done since the promulgation of the
regulations of the PC.
The next project is the Oyster Point
Reservoir Cleanout. We'll be cleaning
out the reservoir while it's still
online using um either divers or drones.
We'll be bidding that project out and
then doing a structural inspection of
the uh of the tank, the reservoir tank.
And our last project um we basically
summarized a lot of small water projects
within the collect within the
transmission and distribution system the
plants um to to kind of roll it up. So
we wouldn't be into multiple pages.
So water has significant investment.
It takes a lot to treat water.
>> Thank you very much. Um and it every
time I see these numbers I'm reminded of
exactly how much we have invested into
this this resource. So thank you for
that counselors. Anything on the last uh
set of slides.
Thank you very much. Um this unless
there's anything that you would like to
add at the end. Uh it is a public
hearing so we will hear any comments
from the public but I just want to make
sure you had an opportunity to finish
your presentation if there was anything
else.
>> Th this does conclude the presentation.
>> I do ask that people um if there's
things that you want presented in a
different way as we go forward. We're in
the process of building the foundation
of how we talk about the capital
planning process and how you want to
receive data and information.
>> Great.
>> So we we want to be careful about that.
>> Thank you very much. Yes. So this is a
public hearing on the capital budget. So
um comments around presentation of
information uh would be appropriate at
this point. If there are any uh folks
can uh join us at the microphone there.
Uh you'll need to turn it back on and
anyone who's sitting here will turn
their mics off while that's so we don't
get cross. That's our theory.
Are there any comments on the capital
improvement plan hearing? Council
President, well, the public makes their
way up. Sure. If I may, just wanted to
express my gratitude to the public works
team for putting this presentation
together and uh clearly for all the work
that you guys do on a day-to-day basis.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Uh for those making public comment this
evening, I'll reiterate from earlier.
Please begin with your name, block of
residence, and uh three minute timer.
Good evening.
>> Evening. Tony Dashra, 700 block of New
Holland Avenue.
So, it's greatly ironic that tonight we
hear the capital budget hearing when,
as we just heard, water is expensive and
the public's looking at a massive data
center, which sure it may initially be
air cooled, but these sort of systems
unregulated
may produce great burden to our water
system. And since water is expensive,
what can not only the rateayers of
Lanster City, but the rateayers of the
entire area serviced by the city expect
if there is a massive use that's going
to use a considerable amount of water?
If we don't put in place now regulations
to ensure that they if they're going to
be water cooled use non-pottable water,
regulations like that could maybe even
be advantageous to meeting our consent
decree. We have hundreds of thousands of
gallons we have to reduce. And this
private investment that's coming to our
community, which has very little regard
for what we need as a public, there's
nothing in place to protect us. This
whole presentation is valued, but it's
terrifying in the face of these private
investments that are going unregulated.
So I am curious if the public works
department has been made aware of these
plans and if so when.
Those are my comments and questions.
Thank you.
>> Thank you Mr. Dastra.
>> Any additional comment excuse me on the
capital improvement plan specifically.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening. Um Taylor Raymond 500
block of St. Joseph Street. Is this
presentation going to be available on
the website?
Um, that's all I've really I might have
one followup question.
>> Um, is it possible that this would be
I'm assuming it will be on the public
works.
>> Yes.
>> Okay, that was everything. Thanks.
>> Thank you.
>> Yes. Similar to how the original list of
projects was made available on June
30th, this presentation can also be made
will will also be made available as
well.
>> I appreciate that. Thank you. Any
additional public comments on the
capital improvement plan? Good evening.
>> Hi again, Emma Burgess, 600 uh West Vine
Street. Uh my comment is I came here to
uh yell about the AI data center data
center and I heard this presentation as
well and I loved it. Um so thank you for
giving that. I learned so much. That's
my comment. Thank you public officials.
>> Thank you.
It's It's not all sexy, but I mean, I
think the waist water stuff is
fascinating. So,
that whatever that says about me, but
thank you for that. Any additional
comments on the hearing?
>> I'm sorry.
>> Yes. So, uh, the the rest of our agenda
will proceed, including our legislative
agenda, which we have not yet gotten to
tonight. I'll remind everybody, um,
second public comment period, report of
the mayor, council comments, and
adjournment. So, yes, if there are no
other comments for the capital
improvement hearing, uh, we will close
it and I will thank you all for your,
uh, your hard work and dedication on
this. Um, as I'm listening to this, I'm
reminded that other cities don't have
this type of planning in place and it is
we are fortunate uh to be able to think
this far ahead. So, thank you. I'll
leave it at that.
>> Very much. We really appreciate the
opportunity to make it as transparent as
practical to the public what we do and
how we do it.
>> Thank you,
councilors. The next item on our agenda
is interimm reports of committees of
council of which we have none this
evening. So we will move then into our
legislative agenda. The first item is
resolutions.
Making sure that Mr. Harris has the
screen the screen back up and that he's
ready
of which we have one this evening. The
uh the one and only is administration
resolution number 52 2025. When you're
ready, Mr. Harris.
>> Yes, madam president. a resolution of
the council of the city of Lancaster
authorizing the filing of an application
for funding through the Commonwealth
Financing Authority Multimodal
Transportation Fund Program in an amount
not to exceed 2.8 million.
>> Motion to approve.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second and I
apologize. I don't recall if this is
coming up through public works or
finance.
>> Public works.
>> Public works. Council Hirs. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Council President. Um this
resolution authorizes the city of
Lancaster to enter into a grant uh
application uh to apply for the grant um
through the Commonwealth Financing
Authorities multimmoal transportation
fund. Um this is in relation to uh the
eastbound connector which is um
in the interim going to be a series of
uh bike lanes and routes that get uh
going eastward out of the city um to to
Konosoga Pines Park. Um and then
ultimately the plan is to get to the
goat path from there um out in East Land
Peter Township. Um the amount is uh for
this grant not to exceed uh $2.8
million. Um if you recall in our
committee that had not been established,
but it is entered into here. Um and the
only other comment I'll add, um correct
me if I'm wrong, Director Campbell, but
I believe uh this is in uh almost as a
followup to previous grant funding we
had received. Um and we were actually
asked to or invited to apply again. Um
which is exciting and and um the city is
you know obviously coordinating with
Mayhem Township and Lancaster Township
as well because they are also involved.
Um, and I think from what I've gathered
in our conversations, Director Campbell,
it's going to be a lot of um, again
interim strategy towards a longer term
project of how to make that connection
work because it's it's definitely
complicated between getting through the
Konosoga River um, and some of the other
obstacles in that particular area. So,
this is um, hopefully going to go
towards connecting.
>> Thank you very much, Councelor Hirs.
Director Campbell, if you have anything
additional.
>> Yes, thank you. I'm often amazed at how
well you you are able to encapsulate the
the core of what we're what we're doing
here. This is in fact um the the
implement this would in fact be the
implementation dollars to actually do
the construction. We have money that
we've we've put together from previous
grants and from the 2022 bond and 2025
bond to be able to to do the design work
and work with the adjacent
municipalities.
This is part of trying to complete or or
finish off some of the connections
between the city's active transportation
network infrastructure and the county
active transportation network as well.
This is what's going to make Lancaster
that much more magical as a place to
live, work, and play.
So, I just wanted to give a little bit
of that as an enhancement to the to what
you had described. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much, Director Campbell.
Counselors, um, are there any additional
comments on the resolution?
Comments on the resolution from the
public?
hearing. None. Mr. Harris.
>> Mr. M.
>> I.
>> Mr. Roya.
>> Mr. Cle.
>> I.
>> Miss. Craig.
>> Hi,
>> Miss Diaz.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Harsh.
>> President Vega.
>> I.
Thank you. That concludes our
legislative agenda for this evening. Uh,
will take us to our second public
comment period. This is open for comment
on issues not previously on the agenda.
Duration of comments is limited to three
minutes per speaker. Uh for those
wishing to make public comment during
this period, please proceed to the
microphone at this time. Begin with your
name and block of residence for our
meeting record.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening. My name is Julie Zug and
I'm living at the zero block of East
Walnut Street.
And um I came here planning only to
listen and learn um with some concerns
about the data center. Um these are just
a few of the
puzzle pieces I've picked up this
evening.
Um, now
the proposed location of the data
center,
um, the LSC communications property on
Greenfield Road, was recently reported
as being the other LSC communications
property on Harrisburg Pike, which is
Lancaster City. But Greenfield, if I'm
not mistaken, is Lancaster Township.
>> It's not.
>> It's in the city.
>> Okay. I was looking at
>> it's on the line between East Lamp Peter
and the city.
>> Okay. All right. Um however um
this property is located according to
the maps I've looked at um on Greenfield
Road. However, it's
across the street from the Knosoga Pines
pool, which the city appears to be ready
to study into relocating,
but still it's included in consideration
of the capital budget
um for their uh for the eastbound
connector plan. And I'm not sure I
understand how that's working, if that's
part of something that you're planning
on relocating.
Um now the developer of this data center
um machine investment group
uh simple Google search New York-based
real estate investment platform which
according to their own website is
focused on opportunistic distressed and
special situations across the United
States.
They were formed
by former senior executives of Garrison
Investment Group,
a Delaware LLC, also out of New York,
which was sanctioned in September of
2022, for failing to have required
audits performed and to deliver the
audited financials to investors. I would
I would urge
our city and anyone involved in planning
this thing to stop selling our city out
to the to the investment bankers. Thank
you.
>> Thank you.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening. the 200 block of North
Concord Street. And this is about the
data center. Also,
there was a long article.
Thank you. I have a No, I have a
scratchy voice. Anyway, um a long
article in the May 26 25th in Time
magazine about the data center in
Granberry, Texas.
And here ours is also going to be air
cooled. Will there be fans and noise,
excessive and unhealthy noise running 24
hours a day, 7 days a week? Where is all
this electricity coming from? Do we have
the local infrastructure for it? And who
is going to be paying for all the usage?
All of us need electricity to run our
houses. What equivalent household usage
in water and power will the data center
be using?
The issue is when the data center
consumes water and electricity, how will
that affect our domestic supply and our
costs just staying in the building's old
footprint at the old printing plant
so that they do not need approval. I
don't really understand the approval
process. seems that we do not have
sufficient information. If we don't know
what's going on, what's happening?
How are we, Lancaster City, going to
deal with it if you have nothing to say
about what's going on
in Granberry, Texas, which is not too
far from Fort Worth, which is a big
city, there have been very strange
medical emergencies from the thousands
of fans emitting a constant buzz. I am
sure our citizens don't want to be
living in some strange unhealthy episode
of the Twilight Zone. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening. Uh my name is Daryl
Legacy. I'm from the 100 block of North
Mary and um I didn't initially come to
see all of the um capital plan, but I'm
glad I did because a lot of it was
actually really interesting and helpful.
Um, and there also are parts of that
that I think apply to the data center.
One of which is spending $400,000 on
Konos Stoa Pines, which is right next
door. And I question how much that park
is going to be used when there are fans
going 247 right next to it. And I think
that's something we should be
considering when we're determining
whether we're going to spend that money.
I also think what's really interesting
to me is that we have to do a land
development plan for buying that one
little strip from PPL, but the data
center doesn't. That means we as the
city are doing a development plan for
ourselves as the city that this external
company does not need to do. I think
that is a huge problem and that's
indicative of what is happening here
that is problematic. I think there
everybody that has spoken has done a
good job already explaining most of the
issues. There are a couple things that
haven't come up. If you go to the
Charissa um website, which they're the
company that's developing this, um they
say Lancaster East, which I assume is
the Greenfield, but they also say
Lancaster West. So even though there's
nothing official, on their website, it
says Lancaster West under development.
You can all go see that right now. So
they are planning what I assume is the
1375 Harrisburg Pike um location.
Regardless of whether they've said they
are doing that or not, they're telling
you on their website they are doing it.
And that is right next to Longs Park.
Like does everybody realize is right
next to Longs Park? So I have some
questions that I think need to be um
considered in addition to the ones that
people have already said. One is who is
going to be responsible to see if they
expand past the existing footprint
thereby triggering the land development
plan, the wastewater treatment plan and
all of these things they are going to
have to do. I mean who's going to be
measuring did they expand past the
existing footprint? I mean it has to be
us. It has to be the city. I don't trust
them. I think and I'm sure they're going
to say, "No, no, we didn't." And I don't
think we should be trusting them on
that. Also, I think we need to think
about um the one especially at
Harrisburg Pike, but probably the one
near uh in Greenfield as well. Have they
done any studies on animal impact? There
are many, many, many migratory birds
that are in Long Park. Are they
affected? Will they be affected by this
semi-secret location that they're
clearly planning to do? And I think
that's something that we need to be
thinking about. I also think we should
be thinking about the impact of
construction. What's going to happen not
only Greenfield but Harrisburg Pike? I
mean, what's going to happen when you're
literally talking next door to Longs
Park, huge construction equipment, I
would assume for years potentially
building this um this location. And I
just think those are extra questions you
should all be asking and we should all
be thinking about. And I don't think we
should be moving ahead until we have
answers. Thank you.
>> Good evening.
>> Hello. Oh, sorry.
>> Am I good? Okay. Um Britney Mitchell, uh
400 block of East Grant Street. Um and I
also wasn't planning on speaking today,
so I'm just gonna kind of go for it and
say what's in my heart. Um I just
hearing
the report from um President Beke uh
with a lot of those really sort of nice
comforting
uh
details about you know the cooling span
and then the and and all the reasons why
the water's going to be okay and all of
that stuff. I just can't help but wonder
what about
our any experience uh that we've had in
in our country with
unmitigated capitalistic self-interest
in an environment that is completely
devoid of any regulations um would make
us think that we should trust or listen
to that. Um something about me is uh I
probably plastics in my brain. Um, most
of you guys probably do, too. Uh, you
know, microplastics are in all of us.
And I'm sure decades ago, those
companies would have said, "Hey,
everything's hunky dory. Check out our
cool fan. We'll write you a nice little
check and whatever else they would have
had to say to get their foot in the
door." And now it's too late. Uh, I
don't know what that's going to do to us
long term. Um, we don't have a lot of,
you know, scientific data on, uh, on
microplastics, but we're still kind of
in that find out era, and it's not
looking good. Um, I don't have any
children, but I care about your kids,
and I'm not willing to sign them up to
be a real time experiment of how much
poison air you can breathe. Um, I hope
that you guys aren't willing to do that
either. Uh, because this is a saying
that once we let it into our community,
we're not going to be able to undo it.
Uh those effects are going to be real.
So, uh I'm not naive. I hope that you
guys aren't either. Um I just hope that
you can, you know, be honest with
yourselves about what you are about to
let in to the community where we all
have to live every day. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Tony Dastra, 700 block of New Holland
Avenue. I'm glad Watergate got brought
up earlier because there's a favorite
song of mine by Stevie Wonder that was
written for Richard Nixon. It's called
You Haven't Done Nothing. First eight
lines go like this. We are amazed but
not amused by all the things you'll say
that you'll do. Though much concerned
but not involved with decisions that are
made by you. But we are sick and tired
of hearing your song telling how you are
going to change right from wrong. Cuz if
you really want to hear our views, you
haven't done nothing.
And that's the case here.
We have an opportunity to let this go
through a use not provided for process
as our zoning ordinance dictates.
Instead, we've said screw all the red
tape. And I think that's insane because
the use that this is provided for. So,
it has additional words behind it that
were not an LMP. One of those being an
exclusion for processing
data is being processed.
I don't care that it's not we can
physically hold. Those storage blocks
and the heat they produce are very real.
This issue is very real. This issue is
very concerning. And if you care about
working families at all, you need to do
something now. You need to speak out now
because people are about to be greatly
hurt financially, their health.
the fact that people have to come to
this board, this board meeting, this
council meeting just to feel like they
have the possibility of being hurt. This
is the same city council I'm frustrated
with for trying to gut the tree
ordinance. Environmental issues have
always been a secondary priority in the
last, I don't know, handful of years. We
have a comprehensive plan that talks
about eco districts. And I'm still mad
at the planning commission, which I'm a
part of, for not amending the zoning
ordinances. To this day, everyone here
should be mad at the planning
commission, too. We have a significant
amount of work to do, but we were too
concerned about giving people city
council districts, things like that.
This is a shame. And the fact that
you're trying to distance yourselves
from this is an important use of words.
Good
evening.
>> Hello.
Um, my name is Christina Sodorescu. I
actually live close to um, Centerville.
Uh, but I, you know, work and live in,
um, Lancaster City. So um I was an
undergraduate and a master's graduate of
Carnegie Melon University where um
coreweave recently announced their
intention to use Lancaster County in
their AI expansion plan. For years as a
student there we weren't just educated
on the beneficial uses of AI. We were
also taught the full picture of all that
comes with AI including the negative
implications that are impossible to
separate from the good stuff.
Um I appreciate your notes earlier today
about um you know the press release that
happened um very recently. Um some part
of me like believes you when you say a
lot of you just recently heard about
this um in terms of the transparency but
it is odd to hear you know the words
transparency and um this surprise update
of uh construction having started
already in the same sentence. Um, so I
kind of wonder what um your response
your accountability um procedures are in
order to make sure that you know those
other parties do um uphold transparency.
Um so with all of this updates um it
feels remarkably fast for something that
will forever change the landscape of our
city. Um so I want to address my
statement to um Lancaster itself, the
city that raised me and the place that
gave me real tangible things to value.
I moved back home um from after living
in a big city after four years of
college
and uh I uprooted my community and life
there uh you know to come back home and
sometimes you don't really appreciate
what you have until you move away and
you can't find it anywhere else. On my
move back, I drove through 44 contiguous
states like hoping that a city would
surprise me and um you know call me to
its home. But nowhere is like Lancaster.
Some of my friends in New York or
Philadelphia come to Lancaster
specifically for the amazing dairy, for
the fresh fruits and vegetables that
come at an unbeatable price. Some of my
friends in Los Angeles asked me to flip
the camera when I FaceTime them because
they can't believe, they can't fathom
how close I live to agriculture and
nature day by day. The fields, the
pastures, the silos, the bucolic
scenery, the backyards, the nature
trails, the central market, the Amish
people. This is my love letter to you,
Lancaster.
And it is my love that I ask everyone to
consider. Do we really need to force
ourselves to be on the map as it relates
to higher tech jobs? Why should we
sacrifice what makes us honest? What
makes what increases the quality of our
lives in order to perpetuate a faster
and frankly crappier lifestyle? Um what
good is, you know, a single, you know,
few billion dollar investment when it
sacrifices the multi-billion annually on
agriculture, food processing, tourism,
and other related sectors? I'm really
happy Memphis came up earlier um because
that Colossus computer uh has access to
50 megawatts of energy um and they you
know were petitioning to try to get to
up to 150.
>> I appreciate your comments but we've
reached three minutes.
>> Okay. Ours is 100 and it goes to 300. So
>> thank you.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening. Taylor Raymond 500 block
of St. Joseph Street. Um, I'd like to
first start by saying that I agree with
several uh community members who have
come up and uh requested a change in our
zoning laws to uh exclude the data
center as uh the wholesale trade and
storage. Um
some place like this needs significantly
more oversight than it has. Um
there the data centers uh will
Sorry. They contribute to uh a rise in
um greenhouse gases like CO2. Um because
as the the growth of AI uh continues to
rise um we cannot keep up with
sustainable energy um to cover the
difference. Um so it's going to uh
increase the effects of climate change
uh locally and globally.
um which is going to have uh an outsized
impact on our poorest residents
including the ones who live outside. um
they are
uh
not very regul uh very well regulated by
any government but there are some
governments that we can look to um for
uh the for groundwork essentially
notably Ireland um the EU AI act um and
uh the Senator Ed Marky who's a Democrat
he's pushing for more info and
sustainability on AI I um I think that
we should be following suit um and we
shouldn't allow this data center. Um I
uh as I said at the last city council
meeting, I work at the Lancaster County
Tax Collection Bureau, which is less
than a mile as the crow flies um from
the Greenfield Road uh data center um
area. Um, so not only do I live in the
city, I work so clear, so close. Um, and
as you said, uh, it's it straddles the
line of East Lampeder. Um, or yes, East
Lampeder. Um, so it affects not only
city residents, uh, but anybody who
works in the city, anybody who lives or
works in East Lamper. Um, I don't think
that
we should allow this because it affects
so much more than we have any control at
city council over.
Um,
yeah, that is everything I've got. Thank
you.
>> Good evening.
>> Hi, Ellen Sloan. I live in the first
block of North Lime Street. I'm not
going to talk about the data center. I'm
going to talk about something I talked
about two weeks ago and I'll keep
talking about it until I get some kind
of response. Um, I'm here once again to
speak about ICE. As you may be aware,
the budget reconciliation bill signed
into law this month allocates a 45
billion for building new immigration
detention centers, which represents a
265%
annual budget increase. It is a 62%
larger budget than the entire federal
prison system. B almost $30 billion
towards ICE enforcement and deportation
operations, a three-fold increase in
IC's annual budget. All this while also
capping the number of immigration judges
at 800 despite the record backlogs. The
Trump administration means business.
Lancaster calls itself a welcoming city.
Some call Lancaster the refugee capital
of the United States. Who among us here
tonight would deny that immigrants have
enriched our community beyond measure?
We must do what we can to protect the
folks who have come here from places of
pain and struggle looking simply for a
place to live in peace.
I am once again asking the city council
to pass an ordinance a requiring visible
identification for all law enforcement
agents operating within the city,
including federal agents and prohibiting
facial concealment of said officers.
B, banning our local police from
cooperating with ICE agents, especially
without warrants or legal uh clear legal
justification.
and C also to work with city schools and
hospitals to develop protective policies
and rapid response systems when federal
ICE agents show up.
I'm sure you have seen the horrific
videos of people being snatched off the
streets or at courouses or their places
of work by masked individuals with
frightening weapons. Disappeared. No due
process. sent to prisons far away,
perhaps never to see their loved ones
again. We have seen the unwanted
militarization of Los Angeles. Is this
what we want in our city? Secret police
disappearing people. Please act before
it is too late. They are coming for
immigrants now. Who will they come for
next? Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Are there any additional comments for
this period?
Good evening.
>> My name is Robert Mlan, 123 South
Christian.
And I'm here basically I have little
sign showing around. It's called
democracynow.org.
You can get that on your computer. What
you're talking about as far as this AI
in this area is the tip of the iceberg.
You don't have any idea and nobody else
has any idea how it's going to turn out.
This woman Karen Ho wrote the book to
explain it
and it's she's from China
Hong Kong. She's back and forth in the
United States. She has scared the devil
out of the people who have heard her
speech. And you can get a synopsis of
the book on democracy now.org.
Just just hit a and you will get the
whole book in one hour's time. But
everyone should have this and find your
way to examining what she's saying.
She's a Chinese
person who wrote this for over 20 years
of work.
She knows what she's talking about and
we are all going to suffer in the long
run. never get out and it's going to
stop
financially destroy us. There's a
rallies up in northern PA whole valley
for transmission lines big ones
to carry AI line energy
the whole valley the whole valley was
threatened to be condemned
for this AI business
that's what's happening around the
world. This is an international station
around the world. It's happening around
the world. Not just in this area,
the whole world is suffering.
just
just on the beginning of all
I will encourage you.
>> We will actually the easiest way to get
that to us is through Mr. Harris and he
will give us that send us that
information. Thank you so much. Are
there any additional comments for this
period?
Hearing none, we will close the second
public comment period. Thank you again.
Uh the next item on our agenda is the
report of the mayor, mayor Sarra.
>> I don't have a report this evening given
uh the late hour. Thank you very much.
The next item was the report of the
president of council which I delivered
at the beginning of the meeting and the
last item then before adjournment is
council comments. Councilors, any
comments this evening
>> outside of our agenda? Councelor Amed?
>> Uh thank you council president. Um and
uh as this um is an ongoing issue where
we are learning more each day, um I
would hope that council can receive a
report um on what options council does
have, what are uh the current situation
regarding the data centers uh to help
make sure that council um knows what we
can do to uh protect the city's
interests moving forward and also
alleviate some of the concerns that uh
community members have shared. So um
thank you and that concludes my
comments.
>> Thank you councelor Med. Any additional
council comments
>> hearing none. Having reached the
conclusion of our agenda councilors I'll
hear a motion to adjurnn.
>> Motion to adjurnn. We
>> have a motion and a second. All in
favor?
>> I I we are adjourned. Thank you.